<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>English protestants plea, and petition, for English preists [sic] and papists to the present court of Parlament, and all persecutors of them: diuided into two parts. In the first is proued by the learned protestants of England, that these preists and Catholicks, haue hitherto been vniustly persecuted, though they haue often and publickly offered soe much, as any Christians in conscience might doe. In the second part, is proued by the same protestants, that the same preistly sacrificinge function, acknowledgeing and practize of the same supreame spirituall iurisdiction of the apostolick see of Rome, and other Catholick doctrines, in the same sence wee now defend them, and for which wee ar at this present persecuted, continued and were practized in this Iland without interruption in al ages, from S. Peter the Apostle, to these our tymes.</title>
            <author>Broughton, Richard.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1621</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 188 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 64 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A17013</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 3895.5</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S114391</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99849616</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99849616</idno>
            <idno type="VID">14775</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A17013)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 14775)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 785:16)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>English protestants plea, and petition, for English preists [sic] and papists to the present court of Parlament, and all persecutors of them: diuided into two parts. In the first is proued by the learned protestants of England, that these preists and Catholicks, haue hitherto been vniustly persecuted, though they haue often and publickly offered soe much, as any Christians in conscience might doe. In the second part, is proued by the same protestants, that the same preistly sacrificinge function, acknowledgeing and practize of the same supreame spirituall iurisdiction of the apostolick see of Rome, and other Catholick doctrines, in the same sence wee now defend them, and for which wee ar at this present persecuted, continued and were practized in this Iland without interruption in al ages, from S. Peter the Apostle, to these our tymes.</title>
                  <author>Broughton, Richard.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>1-96, 81-110 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>C. Boscard],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[Saint-Omer :</pubPlace>
                  <date>With permission, Anno 1621.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>By Richard Broughton.</note>
                  <note>Place of publication and printer's name from STC.</note>
                  <note>First part only--STC.</note>
                  <note>Sheets A and B and the inner forme of C are in 2 settings; e.g. title page line 5 ends: "persecu-" or "perse-"; both at Bodleian. This copy ends "perse-"--STC.</note>
                  <note>Running title reads: Protestants plea and petition for priests and papists.</note>
                  <note>Identified as STC 10415 on UMI microfilm.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Catholics --  England --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Persecution --  England --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2008-01</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2008-01</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-01</date>
            <label>John Latta</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-01</date>
            <label>John Latta</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:14775:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:14775:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>ENGLISH PROTESTANTS PLEA, AND PETITION, FOR ENGLISH PREISTS AND PAPISTS, TO THE preſent Court of Parlament, and all perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cutors of them: diuided into two parts.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>IN THE FIRST IS PROVED by the learned proteſtants of England, that theſe Preists and Catholicks, haue hitherto been vniuſtly perſecuted, though they haue often and publickly offered ſoe much, as any Christians in conſcience might doe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>IN THE SECOND PART, IS PROVED by the ſame proteſtants, that the ſame preiſtly ſacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficinge function, acknowledgeing and practize of the ſame ſupreame ſpirituall Iuriſdiction of the Apoſtolick See of Rome, and other Catholick doctrines, in the ſame ſence wee now defend them, and for which wee ar at this preſent perſecuted, continued and were practized in this Iland without interruption in al ages, from S. Peter the Apoſtle, to theſe our tymes.</p>
            <q>
               <p>
                  <hi>Odio habuerunt me gratis.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>They haue hated me without cauſe.</p>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>With permiſsion, Anno</hi> 1621.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="preface">
            <pb facs="tcp:14775:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:14775:2"/>
            <head>THE PREFACE TO AL INDIFFERENT AND EQVALL READERS.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">R</seg>Ight honorable and the reſt, my dearest and moſte beloued contrymen, kinred, and frends: I haue by the greate pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uidence, protection and mercy of God liued now amongst you, a preiſt in perſecution, little leſſe then halfe the life of an aged man: That which re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mayneth, is cheife my debt by nature to dye, and make accompt to my higheſt Kinge, and Iudge, as of late our moste reuerend Arch-preist within theſe few weekes hath done: whoe (as I interprete his letters) bequeathed as a legacie to mee vnworthie, this chardge: To write, and publish to the world this en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſueing treatiſe, which I name. <hi>The proteſtants Plea, and petition to the parlament for preiſts, and papiſts:</hi> (ſoe many protestants pleaſe to ſtile Catholicks. If this chardge had not beene committed vnto mee by my ſoe honored and reuerend frend, yett hauinge beene ſoe longe a partaker of the miſeries which english catholicks haue in theſe tymes endu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, and beeing well acquainted with the proceedings of bothe ſides, and knowing by certaine experience, that beſides their ſufferings to their immortall ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nor, their published bookes by diuers our learned preiſts haue ſoe conuinced the vnderſtandings of our
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:14775:3"/>
greateſt aduerſaries in all cheife questioned things. That noe proteſtant Bishop or other writer hath now after diuers yeares made any answeare at all vnto them: and of many former moste humble petitions of our learned preiſts and catholicks, both to our pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtant princes, and parlaments, to haue audience in diſputation with their best learned proteſtant Bis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hops &amp; doctors, whether to thy could conuince vs as guiltie and worthie to bee perſecuted, as we haue beene, which hither they would neuer graunt, but haue ſoe longe and greuouſly without any triall or condemnation, executed and perſecuted vs in ſoe straunge a maner: and the preſent protestant rather puritane parlament, ſtormeth now more against vs, then the wiſest of vs can ſee reaſons to warra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t them: I therefore for the honor of God, and reputation of his holy church and Religion, the loue of my country, and to performe my frends request, doe puplish this remembred worke to bee diuided into two parts, and eyther of them to bee inuincibly proued by the lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned protestants of this kingdome. In the firſt, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the holy ſcripture ſoe deſcribeth the dutie of well lyuing men: <hi>Declina à malo, &amp; fac bonum, declyne from euill and to good:</hi> I am to proue by theſe remembred protestants, that the catholicks of England doe moste religiouſly decline from your Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, and all participating therein, and their of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fers conſidered, the protestant ſtate doth moſte vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iuſtly perſecute them. In the ſecond, to iustifie, that <hi>fac bonum,</hi> wee doe well, and therein performe the holy commande of God, in profeſsing the catholicke
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:14775:3"/>
Religion, the ſame with the church of Rome, shall bee demonstratiuely proued by theſe protestants, and the best Antiquities and monuments they haue of our firſt true Apostolick Religion, in theſe kingdomes of our preſent most honored ſoueraigne kinge Iames, that not onely thoſe cheifest questions, for which wee ar ſoe perſecuted, as namely holy preisthood, now treaſon, the ſacrifice of the maſſe ſo punished and the ſpirituall power, and iuriſdiction of the ſee Aposto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licke, here nowe ſoe penall and contemptible, but if need require, all other controuerſies betweene vs of ſubstance, haue euer from the tyme of S. Peter the Apostle, in euery age, and hundred yeares, vntill theſe dayes beene practiſed and continued here, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out interruption, in ſuch ſence, maner, &amp; meaneinge, as wee catholicks of this kingdome with the church of Rome now doe profeſse. And here I entreate noe Religious order to take my Title, <hi>plea and petition for preiſts and papiſts,</hi> as any excluding of their holy labours, and deſerts, which I embrace and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerence: for although I will maintaine for them, that monasticall life in England is ſoe auntient, as the dayes of S. Ioſeph of Aramathia, whoe brought it hither, and dyed here, with his holy company in that profeſsion: yett I finde wee had both preists, and Bishops here, in, and of this nation, longe before that tyme, and many Catholick Christians of the ſame Religion wee now profeſſe, and ſoe continued vntill this tyme without the least diſcontinuance or totall interruption; which I dare not to affirme of our Religious men, ceaſing for an hundred yeares
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:14775:4"/>
after S. Ioſephs death: and in the beginninge of Queene Elizabeths tyme for twenty yeares allmost together, fayled here, when many holy preiſts were laboureing here in this holy worke: and after ſome Religious men of the ſocietie had come hither, they went and left vs alone for diuers yeares. Therfore to ſpeake conſequently (which I muſt performe) I muſt giue this happie prerogatiue to our reuerend preists, whoe neuer fayled or fainted in this cauſe and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try. They were the firſt conuerted this kingdome, and did neuer ceaſe. They first tooke this quarrell in hand in the tyme of Q. Elizabeth, and onely were they, that neuer gaue it ouer. They are principally they, whoe in the catalogues of our holy writers of this tyme, ar stiled with that honor. They ar the ſpirituall fathers, and in Christ Ieſus haue begotten, both the preſent Religious and other catholicks of this king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome. They, whoe with their holy doctrine, and effu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of their ſacred blood, for this moſte glorious cauſe, haue aboue all others (eight or more to one) beene the continuall preachers and propugners of this true faith with vs. They (whoe both in the preſence and abſence of all religious) haue often offered and humbly ſought, publick defence thereof by diſputa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion against the beſt learned and ſelected protestant Bishops and Doctors of this nation. Therefore leauinge theſe peculiar honors vnto the Reuerend preiſts of England, I will with ſuch inequallitie as I haue before propoſed, maintaine for all preists, Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligious, and all catholicks, that our holy preist<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood, ſacrifice of Maſſe, ſpirituall Romane iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſdiction,
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:14775:4"/>
and the like were vſed and continued <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ere without chaunge, or intermiſsion, in the ſame <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>enure wherein Catholicks now profeſſe them, from S. Peter to theſe dayes, by our protestant war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rants and Antiquities. And ſoe I rest</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your moſt loueinge and well wiſhing contry man.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="treatise">
            <head>TO THE RIGHT HONORABLE Court of parlament: eſpecially ſuch as therein bee perſecutors of Catholicks: and to all other ſuch perſecutors.</head>
            <head type="sub">A Breuiate of the vndoubted truthe of catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick Religion perſecuted in England.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Right honorable, and the reſt.</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He penalties, and perſecutions, which in theſe daies of Proteſtants, haue been heaped vpon, and proſecuted againſt the ſacred preiſts, and renowned Catholicks of England, haue beene ſoe heauy, and greate by his Maieſties regall ſentence, in publice par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lament, that they moued him, to theſe words of commiſeration. <hi>My mynde was euer free from perſecution, or thrallinge my ſubiects in matters of conſcience: I was ſoe far fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> encreaſing their burdens with Roboham, as I haue ſoe much, as either tyme,
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:14775:5"/>
occaſion, or lawe could permitt, lightned them</hi>
               <g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Your Courte well knoweth, what the caſe of Roboham was (wee neede ſay noe more, and what other heauie burdens haue been ſince then heaped vpon vs; And by your preſent aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſemblie now againe to bee inuented and ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded. <hi>in his publick ſpeach in his 1. parlam.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>You cannot poſsibly bee ignorant what an eminent man in your houſe, and companie, hath written of the opinion of the chriſtian world, of theſe proceedings: The <hi>ſuffrings</hi> (Syr Edwyne Sandes ſpeaketh vnto you, <hi>in his booke of the relation of the ſtate of Religion) and martyr<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domes of English catholicks in theſe times, ar ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compted to the height of Neroes, and Diocleſians perſecutions, and the ſuffrings on their ſide, both in meritts of cauſe, in extremitie of torments, and in constancie and patience, to the renowned martyrs of that heroicall church age.</hi> What <hi>Nero,</hi> and <hi>Dio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſian</hi> were, amonge the greateſt tyrants, and perſecutors, your place, and lawe-makers may not pleade ignorance; neyther what the honor and glory of that moſte ſacred preiſthood, ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifice and Religions, which ſoe vehemently, and beyonde example, you perſecute. If all ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholicks would bee ſilent, your owne proteſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tant Biſhops and Antiquaries haue publiſhed in Theaters, &amp; hiſtories to the preſent world, and future poſterities, that the very ſame were planted and embraced here, in the Apoſtles tyme, and were neuer chaunged in any mate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riall
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:14775:5"/>
thinge, vntill your pretended reformatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. <hi>Protest. Bishops in the Theater of Brit. l. 6. Holinsh. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>iſt. of Engl. in Claud. Cambden in Britan. Godwyn Conuerſ. Parker. antiq. Brit. Grymsto<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> booke of Eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>es in Engl. Scotland, Ireland.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Yf wee appeale to kings and parlaments, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> whereon you builde,) all the auncient parla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, lawes, &amp; liues of the kings of Scotla<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ry out vnto vs, that after 80. Chriſtian kings <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>here, king Iames is the firſt, and onely pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eſtant kinge. The parlaments, lawes, liues of kings, and hiſtories of England, and Ireland doe publiſh vnto vs, that of all his primogeni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ors kings of theſe nations, hee alone is pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtant kinge of them. Hee claymeth nothing from king Henry 8. Edward 6. or Q Elizabeth <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ee enioyeth, (and longe and happily God graunt him to enioy it) this Empire by a bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>er and truer right, then they could giue him. <hi>Hector Boeth. Vereca &amp; alij hiſt. Scot. all English &amp; <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rish hiſt. with their parlam. &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Your hiſtories and the laſte wills and teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of thoſe kings, ar witneſſes againſt the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> and your Religion, that they laboured moſte <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>niuſtly againſt the lawe of God, and nature <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>o ſuppreſſe the vnqueſtionable right of our ſoueraigne, and his holy mother. <hi>(Edw. Howes preface hiſtorial in king Henr. 8. laſt will of king Henr.</hi> 8.) All thoſe lawes, parlaments and anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quities ar warrant, that from our firſt conuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to Chriſt, wee had noe other Biſhops,
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:14775:6"/>
preiſts, miniſters, or church ſeruice, which you call communion, but Romane catholicke Biſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hops, preiſts (whom you make Traytors) and ſacrifice of maſſe, for the liuinge and the dead, now ſoe perſecuted by you, vntill the ſecond parlament of kinge Edward 6. a childe, moſte childiſhly began this innouation. (<hi>Parlament 2. Edw. 6. cap. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. &amp; an. 5. c. 1. Confer. at hampt. court.</hi>) And in Scotland your miniſtry and communio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> deuiſed there by that Traytor to God, and prince, is of a yonger ſtandinge, in the yeares 1560. and 1571. (<hi>Commun. booke &amp;c. of the kirke of Scotland by Iohn knoxe 9. of march. an. 1560. and 1571.</hi>) Your proteſtant Antiquaries muſtar vnto vs about 1000. approued claſsicall writers, in this kingdome that be renowned in the chriſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tian world; whoe were ſuch preiſts, ſaid maſſe, preached and proued that Religion they tell vs of many thouſand Biſhops by continuall ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſsion from our firſt chriſtianitie, of aboue 1000. canonized Saints, of diuers thouſands of Religious men and woemen, liuing in conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuall pouertie, chaſtitie, and obedience, ſince the tyme of Saint Ioſeph of Arimathia, that bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ryed Chriſt, and brought monaſticall life into this kingdome, wee had 700. Religious how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes founded for them, which you haue defa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced. <hi>Baleus l. de Scriptor. centur. 1.2.</hi>3.4. <hi>Ioh. Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land. de ſcript. Pitſeus de vir. illuſtrib. aetate 2.3.4.5. &amp;c. Capgrau. &amp; al. de Sanct. histor. Angl. paſsim. Theater of Brit. per tot. Stowe hiſt. Holinsh. histor.
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:14775:6"/>
Eng. Scot. Irland. Camb. Britan.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Our Religion builded thoſe churches which <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ou haue reſerued, &amp; many thowſands which <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ou haue defaced; Wee enioyed aboue the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hird part of England to our Religion 600. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eares paſte, and after wee had more kings, Queens, and princes Saints in this Iſland, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>reland, by your owne hiſtoryes and kale<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ders, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hen there euer were ſince in all the world of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>our Religion. (<hi>Tom. 1.2.3.</hi>4. <hi>Concil.</hi>) Our Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion had for external warra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t aboue 20. general <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ouncells. From the firſt of nyce in the time of Conſtantine, our Kinge, Emperour, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ryman, and Sardyce, where the popes ſuprea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>acy, maſſe, and preiſthood are confirmed, <hi>Concil. Nic. 1. can. 6.7. Sardic. concil. Theater of Bri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>an. in Brit. Stowe hist. Holinsh. ib. Camb. Brit.</hi> which our brittiſt biſhops receued, vntill the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>aſte of Trent in the tyme of Q. Elizabeth to which our catholicke Biſhop Pates of worceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>er, ſubſcribed for England for vs, and againſt you, as your proteſtant Biſhop telleth vs. (<hi>Godwyn. Catalog. of Bish. in worcester in Rich. Pates</hi>) wee had conſequently all holy fathers, and Biſhops preſent in them to warrant vs. wee had, and haue, as your proteſtants ack<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nowledge, <hi>(Caſaubon. reſponſ. ad Cardinal. Peron. pag. 69.70.)</hi> all Apoſtolicke ſeas for vs, againſt you. wee had and haue conſequently, all thoſe true, and vndeniable motiues of true Religio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, which moued the chriſtian world, to embrace
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:14775:7"/>
the lawe of Chriſt, to aſſure and confirme v<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> in this truthe, wee ſee and knowe that this our holy faith accordinge to the foretelling of Chriſt, his prophets, and Apoſtles, is preached and planted in all the worlde, Europe, Africke, Aſia, and America, neuer any Religion in the lawe of nature, of Moyſes, Iewes, Turcks, Tar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tares, proteſtants, pagans, or other, is, or was at any tyme in any degree dilated, as it is. <hi>Grymston Booke of estates in k<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> of Spaine, Europe, Aſia, Africk, America.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And for externall ſplendor at home, it was ſoe greate, when king Henry 8. began to enuie the glory of it, that he promiſed the parlame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t (as your proteſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t hiſtories aſſure vs, if it would graunt him power to viſitt the Religious how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes: <hi>Hee would create,</hi> (your proteſtants words) <hi>and mayntayne 40. Earles 60. Barons 3000. knights, and 40. thowſand ſouldiers with skilfull captaines and competent mayntenance for them all for euer, out of the auntient church reueneues, and the people should bee noe more charged with loanes, ſubſidies and fifteens.</hi> Of all theſe bleſſings, and benefites wee are ſpoyled, and by your Religion depri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued; And not onely wee, that now bee catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licks in England, but all faythfull ſoules all<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready departed out of this world, and thoſe that ar not yet borne, if they ſhall bee of the poſteritie of thoſe holy founders, to bee prayed for, to the end of the world, by thoſe Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gious fowndations, and al pore hungry bodyes
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:14775:7"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ere releiued with thoſe donations, which <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>oteſtant tymes haue conuerted to vanities, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>d that which is vnchriſtian, to perſecute the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eligion, which fownded theſe holy howſes. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nd with ſuch vehemency and cruelty wee ar <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>erſecuted, as you haue before acknowledged, our lawes, records, regiſters, &amp; our miſeries, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>alamities, and martyrdomes haue publiſhed <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>o all the world. <hi>Edw. howes in his historial pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>reface in kinge Henry 8.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>All this you doe vnto vs, vnder pretence <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hat wee will not forſake our holy Religion <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>oe firmely, and vndoubtedly proued, by ſoe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>any vndeniable teſtimonies, in your owne <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>udgments, that wee cannot bee deceaued, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ept God (which is vnpoſsible) can deceaue <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s. And in remayninge and perſiſting wherein, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nd following and frequentinge that order, which it preſcribeth, the ſacrifice and Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments which it vſeth, wee ſhall by your beſt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>earned proteſtants writing, with your publick <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>riuiledge, bee ſure to bee ſaued, when contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ywiſe if wee ſhould bee ſoe graceleſſe, as for <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eare of torments, and afflictions, to harken vnto you in matters of Religion, the ſame your <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eſt learned proteſtant Biſhops, and others aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ure vs agayne, wee ſhall come into a fallible, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eceaueable, and actually erroneus Religion, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nd conſequently ſhall bee damned for euer. <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>oue prot. Bish. perſuaſ. Feild l. of the church pag. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>7.182. Couel. def. of Hooker pag. 68.73.76. Feild
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:14775:8"/>
pag. 69. willet Antilog. pag. 144. Theater of grea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Brit. Saxons. Sam. Daniel. hist. &amp;c. Feild pag. 20<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Iſaac Caſaub. praef. reſponſ. ad Gard. Peron. Do<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> perſuaſ. Morton Apolog. part. 2. pag. 315. will<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Antilog. praef. to the Read. vniuerſities answeare <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> the mill. pet. Confer. at Hampt. pag. 47. Proteſt. R<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> lat. of that conference printed by Ioh. windet in thr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ſeuerall copies 1.2.3.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And if God and the truth of his holy cauſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> mayntayned in our bookes, againſt you, ha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> not inforced and neceſsitated theſe your pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blicke writers, thus publickly to condemn<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> you, and forwarne vs from communicating<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> with you, in theſe affaires: yett the lamentable and deſolate experience it ſelfe in your parla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of king Henry 8. k. Edward 6. Q. Eli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zabeth &amp;c. crieth out vnto the world, that all the parlaments and princes ſupreame heads of Religion by you, haue beene deceaued, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceaued all, that followed them in theſe things. Kinge Henry 8. was the firſt, (<hi>parlament of k. Henr.</hi> 8. <hi>after an. Reg. 22.</hi>) and was herein con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to all antiquitie, contrary to k. Edward his ſonne (<hi>parlam. Edw. 6.1.2.3.)</hi> daughter Eliza<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beth (<hi>parlam. 1. Elizab. iniunctionis of Q. Eliz. an. 1.</hi>) and kinge Iames. (<hi>Articles of Relig. ann. 1562</hi>) and to himſelfe by diuers parlaments, and his Religion dead with him, and condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned by you. Kinge Edward was contrary to his father, his ſiſter, to you, and to himſelfe in diuers publicke parlaments, and his publick
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:14775:8"/>
iniunctions. Queen Elizabeth was in the ſame <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſe of contradiction, to her father, brother, to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>u, and herſelfe by publicke practice, parla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ent, proclamations, and iniunctions, in leſſe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>me then three quarters of one yeare. And <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>uchinge that peece of her firſt parlament, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>herein ſhee condemned the maſſe, there was <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ot one diuine, Biſhop or other, that gaue co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ent or could giue it vnto her, but all againſt. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nd their extrauagant proceedings therein, were ſuch, as they bee related by your owne <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ntiquaries, Cambden, Howes, and others, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hat Paganiſme, Turciſme, Epicuriſme, Iudaiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ne, Atheiſme, or any other hereſie, might as <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>aſely haue beene ſettled here, as proteſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tiſme was: which is not here to bee entreated. King <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ames our preſent ſoueraigne is generally ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>en to bee to too wiſe, and learned, to learne Religion of ſuch Tutors. <hi>Cambden in Apparat. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>d Annal. &amp; in Annal. in Elizabeth. Howes histo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>iall preface in Q. Elizabeth and others.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Kinge Henry the 8. deſired at his death, as <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>roteſtant hiſtories ſufficiently inſinuate, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>iuers then liueing in his Court haue teſtified, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>o bee reconciled to the church of Rome, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>n one of his laſte Acts the inſcription of his Tombe, doth playnely omitt, and relinquiſh <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>or euer his pretended ſupreamacie. And in his <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>aſt will and teſtament (<hi>Howes ſupr. in k. Henr.</hi> 8. <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>towe an. vlt. Henr. 8. in his laſte will &amp; testame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t</hi>) <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>rdeyned preiſts, &amp; maſſes, (ſoe odious now,
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:14775:9"/>
and cheifeſt cauſe pretended of our perfection<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 
               <hi>to continue in England to the end of the world, wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>linge and chardgeinge</hi> (the words of his will) <hi>prince Edward his ſonne, all his executors, all his heires and ſucceſſors that should bee kings of this Realme, as they will answeare before almightie God, at the dreadfull day of iudgment, that they, &amp; euerie of them doe ſee it performed. (Exempl. an.</hi> 1. <hi>Edw.</hi> 6. <hi>die</hi> 14. <hi>Februar.)</hi> Kinge Edward 6. was but a child, but both hee and his protectors by which hee was ruled, ſhould haue beene ruled by this will, yet as proteſtants vle to doe, pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently breaking it, for their worldly ends, and breingeing in the proteſtant Religion. (<hi>Foxe to.</hi> 2. <hi>Acts and monum. in k. Henr.</hi> 8. <hi>and an.</hi> 1. <hi>Edw.</hi> 6.)</p>
            <p>The cheife Actor, and Author of thoſe pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedings, the Duke of Northumberland Lord protector, when hee came to dy, renownced proteſtant Religion for hereſie, and as your proteſtant hiſtories tell vs, (<hi>Stowe histor. an.</hi> 1. <hi>of Queen Mary: and others.</hi>) was reconciled vnto, and dyed in the vnitie and faith of the Romane church. For Queene Elizabeth, ſhee, as ſome noble men, and diuers ladyes of honor can in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forme you, and ſome haue ſoe teſtified, died noe good proteſtant, neither could endure the ſight of her proteſtant Biſhops, at that time: &amp; proteſted in her life to the lady Saint-Iohn, widowe to the Lord Oliuer Saint-Iohn of Ble<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſoe, <hi>Deus testis,</hi> ſoe ſhee confidently rela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, and ſaid ſee could ſhew that Queenes let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:14775:9"/>
to that purpoſe, that ſhe would haue liued a Catholike, but for her ouer-ruling Proteſtant Counſaile: naminge ſome of them, no happie members of this kingdome; which your Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>tant hiſtorians giue way vnto, that ſhe did very often, before ſuch men by politick deuiſes with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>rew her from it; frequent <hi>the Sacraments</hi> of Confeſſion, &amp; of the <hi>bleſsed bodie of Christ, Maſſe, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nd the rites of Catholike Religion (Edw. Howes historicall preface in Queene Elizabeth.</hi>) and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eſted in publicke Parlament, <hi>neuer to vexe or <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rouble the Romane Catholikes concerning any dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference in Religion.</hi> Like was the caſe of William <hi>Cecile</hi> Lord Burleigh hir great Counſailor, both <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>or his Religion, in that time; and at his death, charged his ſonne <hi>Robert</hi> Earle of Salisbury, ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>er to perſecute any of that Religion. Thus hee acknowledged to a worthy and noble witneſſe; who, as God is witneſſe, ſo hath teſtified.</p>
            <p>We doe not, we will not conteſt, with our preſent, moſt honoured, wiſe, and learned Soue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raigne; neither enter into his priuate iudgement: But if any the beſt learned proteſtant Archbi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops, or Biſhops you haue, will iuſtifie all thoſe publicke ſpeaches, writings, and bookes which goe vnder the name of our King, to proceede from him; if it will pleaſe him to giue way vnto <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>t, they ſhall haue maintained againſt them, that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>y thoſe publiſhed writings, it is damnable for <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hem to perſecute vs, and we in conſcience can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not, if to gaine a thouſand worlds, be of your
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:14775:10"/>
proteſtant Religion. And we humbly hope this nothing derogateth to his prudent Maieſtie; for we openly and willingly write, that concerning all your beſt learned Biſhops, and others that haue written; as namely <hi>Whitguiſt,</hi> and <hi>Bancroft,</hi> of Canterburie, <hi>Bilſon,</hi> and <hi>Andrewes</hi> of Win<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheſter, <hi>Doue, Barlowe, Godwyne, Field, Bridges, Hooker, Couell,</hi> and all the beſt ſtudents amongſt you, were in iudgement far from perſecution of Catholikes, and as far from aſſurance, that they themſelues were in true Religion. It is no vaine boaſting now to write it; becauſe in all contro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſiall poynts, we haue many yeares ſince in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vincibly prooued it by your beſt learned Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtant Biſhops, and Doctors, (<hi>Protestants Recan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation in matters of Religion. l. 1. &amp; l 2 Protestants Demonſtrat. for Catholikes Recuſancy &amp;c.</hi> both in generall; that neither Scriptures, Traditions, Counſels, Apoſtolike Churches, Fathers, or any authoritie in diuine matters is for you, but all a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt you, that you haue not, neither hereafter by your Religion can poſſibly find any Rule or direction to bring you into trueth: That there is not, nor can be any true and competent Iudge or Conſiſtorie with you to decide theſe conten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, and bring you into the right way. That there is neither true Biſhop, Prieſt, or Cleargie man in your Congregation: That in all particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar queſtions betweene vs, you are in error.</p>
            <p>All theſe things ſo inuincibly prooued by your ſelues, that now after diuers yeares our
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:14775:10"/>
bookes receaue no anſwere at all: And your beſt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>earned are ſo far from taking this charge in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>and, that but for diſgrace of theſe times with <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ou, they would in their liues and health <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ot liue in your wauering religion, but be recon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>iled to the Romane Church, as many of them <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ately at their deaths haue bene. And now in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>his your Parlament time, to moue you and London, to know the trueth, the late Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eſtant Biſhop thereof, Doctor <hi>King,</hi> in his life <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>or external cariage, a great perſecutor of Prieſts <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nd Catholikes, a little before his death did plainely denounce your Religion to be damna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, renounced (as wee had prooued before of all ſuch) that he was any Biſhop or Cleargie man; was penitent for his proteſting hereſie, &amp; humblie at the feete of a Prieſt, whom he had formerly perſecuted, confeſſed his ſinnes, recea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued Sacramentall abſolution at his handes, and was reconciled to the Catholike Romane Church, of which he had in his life bene ſo ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hement a perſecutor. Zealouſly and openly pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſting, there was no ſaluation to be had, out of that holy Catholike Romane Church. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore wee neede not to diſpute theſe matters a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>new.</p>
            <p>But becauſe by the preſent tempeſts you raiſe againſt vs in this your Parlament, we are aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red that your ſtorming perſecutions are not ceaſed, if your wils and anger can maintaine their bluſtrings, therefore we cannot but ſtill
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:14775:11"/>
defend our innocencie, and humbly admoniſh you, that by theſe courſes you offer and doe, &amp; we receaue and ſuffer wrong. And becauſe you ſee and know, you are neither able to inſtruct vs, or your ſelues, perſiſting in perſecution, you fall into that lamentable eſtate, preached vnto you out of Pulpit by your now Archbiſhop of Yorke (<hi>D. Matthewes Serm. before the Parlament</hi>) and in publike Parlament denounced by his Maieſtie: <hi>Perſecution without instruction, is but ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rannie (K. Iames ſpeach in Parlament.</hi>) That you cannot, or vncharitably will not (both leade to that damnable eſtate) we are now euidently to demonſtrate to you, and make knowne to the world for our owne excuſe; which we can doe by no better or more certaine meanes in this caſe, then publiſh and make knowne to our dea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt countrey, that from the firſt beginning of theſe your perſecutions broached and borne in the firſt Parlament of Queene Elizabeth, wee haue in all humble and beſt meanes we could, requeſted, and ſought for inſtruction, from your beſt learned Biſhops, Doctors, and inſtructors, among you, if we be in error, by many and ſun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dry petitions to our proteſtant Princes, Parla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, and others, that were in chiefe place and command, to procure it, if there had bene any in your Religion that could performe it. If you had that could, and would not, your eſtate is more then dangerous, if you haue none, can in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruct vs, which you make apparant, if you ſtill
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:14775:11"/>
perſiſt in perſecution. You heare our King and your Archbiſhop call vnto you: <hi>Correction with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out inſtruction, is but tyrannie.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Therfore in this firſt part of this Proteſtant plea, and petition of your beſt learned Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtants in both parts to be vndeniably proued, &amp; iuſtified by them; wee propoſe ſome of thoſe moſt humble ſuites and petitions we haue by the beſt warrant ſpirituall we had in England, our moſt Reuerend Archprieſt, his learned Prieſts, and chiefeſt renowned Catholikes, pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſented, to procure, and obtaine this inſtruction, in conference and diſputation, with your beſt learned Proteſtant Biſhops and Doctors, and with ſuch vnequall conditions on our behalfe, that except the Catholikes of England had bin aſſured, they were in trueth, and their diſputant Prieſts could not be inſtructed by any the beſt learned in your Religion, they could not in conſcience haue made ſo large and diſaduanta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geous offers vnto you, as their ſeuerall petitions and ſuits will witneſſe: Except you will thinke (to flatter your ſelues) that theſe renowned Prieſts and catholikes, did doubt of their Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion (which their martirdomes and ſufferings for it, do inuincibly reproue) and appeale to you for inſtruction, which you denying and yet ſo perſecuting them, can neuer free your ſelues from that dolefull condition remembred by our gratious King and your Archbiſhop; you will further receaue in this firſt part ſuch iuſte
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:14775:12"/>
and moſt reaſonable and vnanſwereable reaſons by the Religions, and proceedings of all your ſupreame heads in ſpirituall buſines vntill his maieſties time (wherein ſilence will be vſed) King <hi>Henry</hi> 8. King <hi>Edward</hi> the 6. and Queene <hi>Elizabeth</hi>; that as they are ſet downe by your beſt proteſtant writers, we cannot yeelde to you in matters of Religion; neither you in con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience either perſecute vs in theſe things, or your ſelues ſecured in that profeſſion.</p>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Howe Catholike Religion was vniustlye ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſed by Queene <hi>Elizabeth,</hi> not one Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rituall perſon hauing voyce in Parlamente conſenting: no diſputation or ordinarie defence thereof permitted to the Catholike Bishoppes and Cleargie: and their duetifull loyaltie not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withstanding their pietie honoured by their pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>testant enemies.</head>
               <p>IN THE firſt yeare and Parlamente of Queene Elizabeth, when our aunciente holy Catholike Religion was ſo vnholily, and irreligiouſly ſuppreſſed, and the new Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant maner and faſhion, by her authoritie re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceaued, as partly before remembred, from our Proteſtant Hiſtories, and will by them more amplie be declared hereafter: All the Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like Biſhops of England then liuing, ſo farre oppoſed againſt it, that as a Proteſtant Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quarie relateth, obſeruing the willfull and
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:14775:12"/>
indirect proceedings of her, and ſome few of her ſecret Councellours, and aduiſers in that ſo importunat buſineſſe, far aboue the compaſſe, calling, and correction of a yong woman, and laye men, diuers of them vrged to proceede to excommunicate that Queene at that time. (<hi>Cambd. Annal in Elizab. p</hi> 37. But others which preuailed, aduiſed to reſerue it to the Pope of Rome: And they all ioyntly contradicted that innouation, and then and there offered as all proteſtant hiſtorians agree <hi>(Stowe and Howes hist. an.</hi> 1. <hi>Eliz. Holinsh. hist. of Engl. Ibid. Theater of Brit an. 1. Elizab. Cambd. in Annal. ſupr.)</hi> publickly to defend and maintaine by diſputation, againſt all aduerſaries whatſoeuer, their holy profeſſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> and religion, and to that purpoſe aſſigned and appointed theſe diſputants: <hi>The then Bishop of Wincheſter, the Bishop of Lichfielde, the Bishop of Chester, the Bishop of Carlile, who had crowned her, the Bishop of Lincolne, Doctor Cole, Doctor Harpeſfield, Doctor Langdal, and Doctor Chadſey.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But that proteſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t Q. &amp; her fauorites know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the weaknes of their cauſe to be ſuch, and how their chiefeſt champio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s had bene not long before in publike ſchooles at Oxford, in the time of Queene <hi>Marie</hi> ſo ſhamefully conuin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced, by ſome of theſe Catholikes, that they were hiſſed by the learned Auditors, durſt not ioyne with the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in tryal (<hi>Foxe in Q. Mary, Cra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. &amp;c.</hi> But the Parlame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t begining on or about the 23. of Ianuary, they had ſo prepared their way before,
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:14775:13"/>
that almoſt in the beginning of that Parlame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, they obtained their purpoſe, for the receauing their new Religion, and effected that in the very firſt Acte or law of that Parlament (<hi>Statut. an. 1. Eliz. cap. 2.</hi>) and would neuer harken to any mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, or petition for diſputation, vntill the laſte day of March (<hi>Stowe, Howes, Holinsh. &amp; ſupr.</hi>) al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt two moneths after they had thus vtterly excluded the Popes authoritie, and the catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholike religion, vſed and practiſed here in this kingdome, euer ſince the time of Pope <hi>Eluthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rius,</hi> and King <hi>Lucius,</hi> as the catholikes offered in Parlament to maintaine, fourteene hundred yeares togeather, without interruption (<hi>Feckh. orat. 1. Elizab.</hi>) and publicke Maſſe and ſeruice of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>he church to haue bene here ſo long, celebra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted in the latine tongue. And would not then condiſcend to any diſputation at all, except the catholikes would accept, (to write in Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtants words; That <hi>Baconus in Theologicis parum verſatus, pontificus in feſtiſsimus, &amp; ordinis v<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ndex, tanquam iudex praeſideret</hi>: Bacon (<hi>a lay man) vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>skilful in diuinitie most infeſtuous enemy to Papiſts, and perſecutor of their order, should be iudge (Cam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den Annal. pag. 27.</hi>)</p>
               <p>And if we may beleeue the preſent proteſtant Archbiſhop, the director of M. <hi>Francis Maſon</hi> in their booke of conſecration, among ſo many eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſentiall matters controuerſed betweene the Proteſtants and vs, they would not diſpute any one at all, but onelie three, concerning ſome ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>remonies.
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:14775:13"/>
(<hi>Fr. Maſon in praef. of their booke of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecrat. and pag.</hi> 103.) <hi>1. about common prayer in the Latine or vulgar tongue. 2. Of the power of Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches to change ceremonies. The third and last; whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther communion was to be miniſtred in both kindes</hi>: and the triall of theſe three ceremonies to be made by a fourth moſt ſtrange ceremonie, in di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſputation, <hi>onely to be put in writing, within two daies warning at the most, vnum &amp; alterum diem de quaeſtionibus praemoniti</hi>; as your Antiquarie writeth, <hi>and deliuered to their ſaid offenſiue enemy, Sir</hi> Francis Bacon (<hi>Cambden annal. pag. 27.</hi>) A thing ſo ridiculous and vnequal in the iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of all learned and wiſe men, that if it had bene offered before Catholike religion was there condemned, it could not in conſcience, ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther by thoſe learned Biſhops and Doctors, or the moſt learned that euer were in the Church of Chriſt; nor by the holy Apoſtles themſelues if they had then and there bene, be accepted.</p>
               <p>Yet Queene Elizabeth and her aduiſers in this, notwithſtanding that ſhe had in open Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lament before, as before is teſtified by our Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtant writers (<hi>Howes historicall preface in Q. Elizabeth.) openly pronounced that shee would ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer vexe or trouble the Romane Catholikes, concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning any difference in Religion</hi>: in that very parla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, where ſhe ſpake theſe wordes, and made that promiſe, proceeded to cruell penalties, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt thoſe Romane Catholikes; all our holie Biſhops were depriued, impriſoned, or exiled:
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:14775:14"/>
(<hi>Stow hiſtor. an. 1. Eliz. Holinsh. ibid. Cambden An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal. an.</hi> 1. <hi>Elizab. Theatre of Brit. an.</hi> 1. <hi>Eliz. &amp;c.</hi>) So were all other Eccleſiaſticall perſons that would not doe, as pleaſed her. Great forfaitures and puniſhments were impoſed vpon all, that ſhould heare Maſſe, or not be preſent at the new deuiſed ſeruice, (<hi>Parl. an.</hi> 1. <hi>Eliz. cap.</hi> 1.2.) praemunire loſſe of landes goods, and perpetual impriſonment, and loſſe of life alſo, with note of Treaſon to them, that ſhould denie that ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preame ſpirituall power to be in her, which many Proteſtants and learned both then and at this time ſaid, and ſay, ſhe was incapable of. All which notwithſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ding that moſt worthy clear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gie in exile, and priſons at home, ſo caried them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues in all ciuill dutie to that Queene, that they are in that reſpect recommended and ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nored by their greateſt Proteſtant aduerſaries and perſecutors; and for learning and pietie dignified and exalted more by theirs and our enemies, then euer any Proteſtant Biſhops or Miniſters, which inuaded their holy places ſince that time. (<hi>Proteſt. def. of English Iustice. Godwine Catal, in thoſe Bish. Camden in Annal.</hi>) But of this ſtrange innouation of Religion by Q. Elizabeth, I ſhall write more largely from theſe Proteſtants hereafter.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="27" facs="tcp:14775:14"/>
               <head>The vertue, learning, and dutiful loyaltie of the Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minarie or ſecular (as ſome name them) Priestes which came after into England, the vniuſt perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cution of them, and catholikes here, and their moſt christian and religious offers and behauiour.</head>
               <p>AFter Q. Elizabeth had by profane deuiſes &amp; inue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tions of ſome few irreligeous cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellors, ſuppreſſed the auntient catholike religio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of this nation, by ſuch ſiniſter proceedings, as are before inſinuated, &amp; to the wonder of the chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian world, <hi>orbe christiano mirante,</hi> as this Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant chiefeſt antiquarie truely noteth (<hi>Cambden Ann. p.</hi> 39.) for the vnco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſcionable maner, &amp; effe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cting herof: though ſhe had in ope<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Parlame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, as befor proteſted, <hi>neuer to vexe or trouble the Roman Catholikes, co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cerning any differe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce in Religio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> (Hows hiſtorical praeface in Q. Elizabeth</hi>) yet being aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, as the truth was, by her <hi>pauculi intimi, her very few ſecret friends (Cambd. ſupr.)</hi> that except ſhe became a perſecutor, againſt her faith &amp; pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe ſo publikely, and lately giuen, &amp; ſo ioyne craft and violence together, the weaknes of her cauſe was ſuch, and the learning and conuerſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of life, of thoſe her Proteſtant miniſters, whom ſhe muſt imploy in this buſines, ſo vne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quall, and inferiour to the Catholike Biſhops, and Cleargie of England, that no hope of ſuch ſucce<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e as they ſought could bee, except theſe holie and worthie men were depriued, impri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoned, baniſhed, or vtterly one way or other,
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:14775:15"/>
put to ſilence, in ſuch maner, that after their deathes, our moſt ſacred order of Prieſthood, which had continued in this nation here, in honor and glorie, from S. Peter the Prince of the Apoſtles, as we haue made demonſtrance in other places, might vtterly and for euer be a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boliſhed and extinguiſhed, as theſe fewe ſecrete friends of thoſe deſignements open Antiprieſts, or Antichriſtians (for the Religion of Chriſt, cannot be without the Prieſts of Chriſts) plot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted and hoped to effect. Your principall prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtant Antiquarie, thus relateth that cruel Tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gedie. (<hi>Camden in Annalib. pag.</hi> 36.)</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Parlamento dimiſso, ex eiuſdem authoritate, Epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcopis pontificijs &amp; alijs eccleſiasticae profeſsionis iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ramentum ſuprematus proponitur. Quotquot iurare abnuerunt, beneficijs, dignitatibus exuuntur,</hi> 80. <hi>re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctores eccleſiarum.</hi> 50. <hi>prebendarij,</hi> 15. <hi>praeſides Colle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giorum, Archidiaconi.</hi> 12. <hi>totidem decani. 6. Abbates &amp; Abbatiſſae, &amp; epiſcopi</hi> 14. <hi>Omnes qui tunc ſede<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>runt, praeter vnum</hi> Antonium Landauenſem, <hi>ſedis ſuae calamitatem.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The Parlament being ended, by the autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie therof, the oath of the Queenes ſupreama<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie was propoſed to the popiſh Biſhops, and all Eccleſiaſticall perſons, as many as refuſed to ſweare, were depriued of their benefices, digni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, and Biſhoprickes. 80. Rulers of Churches, 50. Prebendaries. 15. Maſters of Colledges, 12. Archdeacons. 12. Deanes. 6. Abbots, and Abba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, and 14. Biſhops; all that then remained
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:14775:15"/>
except one <hi>Anthony</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Landaffe,</hi> the ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lamitie of his See. Theſe Biſhops inferiour in vertue and learning to none in Europe, as your Proteſtants acknowledge (<hi>Maſon lib.</hi> 3. <hi>conſecrat. c. 1. pag.</hi> 100. <hi>Cambd. in Annal. ſup. Stowe hiſtor. an.</hi> 1. <hi>Eliz. Holinsh. hiſt. of Engl. 16.</hi>) thus depoſed and impriſoned, and there to languiſh to death, they thought none could ſuruyue to conſecrate anie more prieſtes for England: and all rulers of our Colledges in our (then renowned) Vniuerſities thus expelled, that would not forſweare them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues in ſuch a ſacrilidgeous manner, they thought themſelues aſſured, we could haue no ſucceſſion of Catholike ſtudents here to enter into that holy prieſtly order.</p>
               <p>But, <hi>non eſt conſilium contra Dominum,</hi> there is no counſayle againſt our Lord. The prophane craft and wylineſſe of a few wicked men, ioy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned with a womans ſpiritual ſupreamacie, was too weake to oppoſe and battaile againſt the heauenly wiſdome and will of God. For a very ſmall number, and thoſe of the meaneſt then, of our glorious Cleargie, tranſporting themſelues to Catholike nations, and by ſuch poore meanes as they could procure, liueing in collegiall di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcipline and order at <hi>Doway</hi> in Flaunders, where our common happie and ſpirituall Nurſe and Mother is, haue ſo wounderfull and far beyond the reach of your proteſtant polycies and ſtrate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gems, to the honour of God, and his holy cauſe, againſt you, multiplied and encreaſed, that the
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:14775:16"/>
number and glory of our renowned publike<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſtiled writers, which in this time haue come from thence, giueth not place to anye age, ſince our firſte conuerſion to Chriſte <hi>(Pitſ. de virg. illuſtrib. Brit. aetate</hi> 16.17.) our holye Martirs violently put to death by your Edictes, and proceedings (<hi>Stowe histor. in Henric.</hi> 8. <hi>Elizabeth. &amp; Iacob. Catalog. martyr. ſub Henric.</hi> 8. <hi>Elizab. &amp; Iacob.</hi> 1.5.) exceede the number, &amp; are not exceeded in glorie by any, that hiſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries amonge vs remember, or whoſe me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mories by iniquitie of times are not remai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, except the <hi>nouenius perſecution,</hi> duringe but nine yeares <hi>(Gyldas de excid.)</hi> ours nine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times as longe) vnder Diocleſian the tyrant. The Religious men of our Nation, all the ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rituall Children of that Mother, are nowe poſſeſſours of manye Religious Colledges, and Monaſteries, vnder Catholike princes, and ſome of them in England, with ſo many of ours, are enrolled in the Catologue of glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous martyrs, and a great number here ſtil work<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in this holy labour with vs. And if to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter into ſcholes with your beſt learned, wee needed their aſſiſtance, wee doubt not, but di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers of them are both wel able, and alſo readie to aſſiſt vs.</p>
               <p>But wee haue euer bene ſo far from either needing or requiring it, of them, that when you gaue vs the greateſt hopes of diſputa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, wee neuer ſent for any of our owne re-<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>enowned
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:14775:16"/>
profeſſors lyuing in forraine nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons: But as true Prieſts of England are the ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſors of Saint Peter the glorious Apoſtle, and his holie Diſciples in this Nation, by a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinued and neuer yett interrupted Hierar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chicall ſucceſſion to this daye, as we will iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtifie againſt your beſt antiquaries, and diuines; and firſte after our Biſhops by you depriued, impriſoned, and perſecuted, vndertooke this quarrell of God in hande againſt you, and gayned many ſoules to Chriſt; and for no crueltie or perſecutions you rayſed, or ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>agerated againſt them, coulde at any time be forced to forſake that holie combate, they had vndertaken: But as true Paſtors they ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uentured, and gaue their liues for the ſheepe of our higheſt ſhepheard and redeemer: ſo to the hazard of the honour of Catholike Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, if Proteſtants could haue put them to foyle, in all theſe miſeries and afflictions, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitute of bookes, conference and harbour, of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentimes to hide their heades, they were euer readie to offer, and entreate for tryall, with vnequall conditions; and ſo vnequall and preiudiciall to the diſputante Prieſtes, and Catholickes of Englande, that except they had beene ſo confidente in their cauſe, that they could not be ouercome, and the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtant Biſhops and Doctors compleately fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed and prouided of all thinges requiſite to ſuch a conflicte, if their quarrell were
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:14775:17"/>
iuſt, had not bene deſperatly diffident in theſe matters; neither might the Catholikes in con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience haue made thoſe ſuits and offers, or theſe proteſtants without damnable ſhame haue re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſed them: as the petitions themſelues will be euerlaſting witneſſe to the world.</p>
               <p>And when the proteſtant ſtate of England had in aboue twenty of the firſt yeares of Q. Elizabeth, afflicted vs with many miſeries, and had put many of our renowned and beſt learned prieſts, M. <hi>Sherwine, Foord,</hi> and others, to whom they durſt not graunt priuate diſputation (in the Tower itſelfe though neuer ſo ſecret) vniuſtly to cruell death: and had vſed M. <hi>Campion,</hi> the glorie of that Societie in England, in ſuch mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, neuer allowing him to defende his owne written booke, though neuer ſo priuatly, vntill by tortures and rackes they had al-moſt depri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued him of his life; and after with many of our learned and holy prieſts, did depriue him there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of; had baniſhed M. <hi>Heywood,</hi> and M. <hi>Parſons</hi> had forſaken England, the three prime Engliſh Ieſuits of that time; And no other religious man either of that, or any other order, but onely prieſts being here; and of them aboue thirtie in priſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in the Tower, Marſhalſea, Kings-bench and other places: About which time, the 27. yeare of her raigne, Queene Elizabeth was ſo vnmindfull of her promiſe made in her firſt par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lament before remembred, that by degrees ſhee clambred vp, to the heigheſt pitch of perſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:14775:17"/>
againſt her Catholike ſubiects, that ſhe im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed twenty poundes for euery moneth ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence, fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that her new ſeruice <hi>(Parl. of Q. Eliz. tit. Recuſancy</hi>) at which to haue bene preſent, had bene damnable ſinne and hereſie, fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> our firſt conuerſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to Chriſt, vntil the yeare of K. <hi>Edward</hi> the ſixt a child, both by the lawes of the whole Catholike Church, and of this kingdome.</p>
               <p>And not content with this, proceeded to that contempt of the Prieſtly dignity of our moſt bleſſed Sauiour and Redeemer, his holy Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles, and all holy Biſhops, and Prieſts ſince their time; that ſhe intended to make it treaſon; and al that willingly receaued ſuch men (as Chriſt our Sauiour commandeth all men to do) vnder a great woe and penaltie of loſſe of libertie, lands, goods, and life alſo, which ſhe after enacted for a law in that Parlament. Whereupon, and for preuention of ſo vnchriſtian proceedings, the chiefeſt catholikes of this nation, with the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent and directio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of their learned ſecular Prieſts, then onely here remaining (and no religious men being at that time, or diuers yeares after in England) humbly prefered to that Queene, in her Parlament time, when ſhee decreed that bloody edict, this moſt chriſtian, and more then equall petition, following word by word.</p>
               <q>
                  <pb n="34" facs="tcp:14775:18"/>
                  <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                     <body>
                        <div type="petition">
                           <head>
                              <hi>TO THE QVEENES MOST</hi> Excellent Maieſtie, the humble petition of her Catholike ſubiectes of England, in the 27. yeare of her raigne, wherein their in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nocencie is iuſtified, and their Religion offe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red to be maintained for holy, againſt all Proteſtants.</head>
                           <p>MOST mighty, and most excellent, our dread Soueraigne Ladie, and Queene: the neceſsi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie of our lamentable Caſe hath emboldned, yea ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſarily enforced vs, your Maiesties Catholike and approoued Loyal ſubiects, to preſent our manifold griefes and miſeries, to the merciful viewe, of your Maieſtie. We could still haue bene contented (as hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therto we haue bene) with ſilence to haue made ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue of exceeding great neceſsities: But now most gratious Soueraigne, the Law of God and nature doth Councell vs, to appeale vnto your moſt excellent Heighnes, our head-ſpring, and fountaine of mercy, for the lightning of ſome heauy yoakes, which by common reporte we haue iuſt cauſe to feare, are in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended shortly to be layed vpon our weakned and wearied neckes.</p>
                           <p>To ſpeake to ſo potent and prudent a Prince, as it may be reported boldneſſe; ſo not to ſpeake in a poore and distreſsed ſubiect, may be deemed guiltines. Wee doe therefore, moſt deare ſoueraigne, with all humilitie and no leſſe ſorrow, cry out and complaine,
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:14775:18"/>
that our afflicted harts haue conceaued an vnſpeak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>griefe: For what wound can be more mortall to the bodie, as treaſonable accuſations to innocent mindes? We your Catholike ſubiects, which hitherto haue bene, and euer will be as well carefull to pleaſe your Maiestie, as not to diſpleaſe almightie God, what la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentable state was euer like to ours, that we poore wretches in diſcharging our conſcience towarde God, are reported of, and that before your ſacred Maiestie, to be euill affected towardes your Royall perſon, and princely dignities, and that vpon the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                                 <desc>•</desc>
                              </gap>yle action and intend of euery lewde perſon, wee must be condemned all for traytors? as it appeareth in bookes daily printed against vs, wherein we are moſt odiouſly tearmed blood-ſuckers, and by vncha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritable exclamations, it is published, that your Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iestie is to feare ſo many deaths, as there be Papists in the land. Would God our harts might be layde o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen to the perfect view of your Maiestie, and all the world; no doubt our thoughts should appeare cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſpondent to the expectation of ſo mercifull a Queene, in all louing, true, and faithful ſubiection, and would giue dewe deſerte of mercie for re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward.</p>
                           <p>For most deare Soueraigne, where our greatest accuſation ryſeth vpon our recuſancy, or abſence from the Church, which hath deuoyded vs of all your wonted graces, and ſpecial fauours, wee take al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighty God to witneſſe, that this our refuſing and abſenting our ſelues is not grounded in vs vpon any contempt of your Maieſties Lawes, or any other will<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:14775:19"/>
or trayterous intent, but altogether vpon meere conſcience, and feare to offende God. This God know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth the ſearcher of all hearts, and to the ende, that our ſincerity and dutifull meaning may appeare the better; we doe proteſt before the face of the eternall God, and Lord of vs all, and doe craue his dread<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full indignation in this worlde, and ſentence of endleſſe dampnation to bee our portion in another worlde, if wee doe practiſe, ſpeake, or write any thinge in this poynte, more or leſſe in reſpecte of anie worldlie pollicie, but onelie as the duety of euerie good Christian Catholike bindeth him. In which opinion, if happelie wee bee deceaued, yet if wee should doe contrarie to that we thinke in conſcience to be right, we may iustly be accomp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted men voyde of all grace and honesty, pretending in shew, and thinking otherwiſe in heart, falſe diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſemblers, hatefull to God and man, and in truth the moſt dangerous and worſt ſubiects that may be in a common wealth, as apteſt to any wicked or deſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rat attempt.</p>
                           <p>No leſſe is verified in the late moste excecrable example of that monſter <hi>Parry,</hi> whoſe deteſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble endeauours, doe giue euidente teſtimonye, that the cruell vypar, euer temporiſing and makinge ship-wracke, of all faith and Religion, hathe thereby at length, loſte both taſte and habite of the grace and feare of God. Let ſuch diabolicall diſsimulation, and trayterous thirſte after hal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed blood, ſinke according to Gods iudgement to their deſerued doome of deepe damnation; we for
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:14775:19"/>
                              <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                                 <desc>•</desc>
                              </gap>ur parts vtterly deny, that either Pope, or Cardinall <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                                 <desc>•</desc>
                              </gap>ath power or authoritie to commande, or licence <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                                 <desc>•</desc>
                              </gap>nie man to conſent to mortall ſinne, or to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                              <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                                 <desc>•</desc>
                              </gap>it, or intende any other acte, <hi>contra ius diui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                                 <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                                    <desc>•</desc>
                                 </gap>um;</hi> much leſſe can this diſloyall wicked and vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naturall purpoſe, by any meanes be made lawe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full; to witte, that a naturall ſubiecte maye ſeeke the effuſion, of the ſacred bloode of his an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noynted Soueraigne: whoſoeuer hee bee therefore ſpirituall, or Temporall, that maintaineth ſo ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parant ſacriledge, wee therein renounce him, and his concluſion as falſe, deuilish, and abhominable.</p>
                           <p>But nowe to returne, to our purpoſed mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, wee doe promiſe, that wee will hereafter be reddie and willing to reſorte vnto Churches, and other places, where publicke exerciſe of pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er is vſed, if the learned nowe aſſembled in con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uocations, hall bee able by ſufficiente groundes of Diuinitie, to prooue to the learned of the catholike Church, that wee (being in Religion Catholike) may without committing mortall ſinne, frequent thoſe Churches, where the contrary religion is profeſſed, and exerciſed. If conſcience onely had not preſſed vs in this point, thoſe of our Religion would neuer haue ſuffered therefore ſo many diſgraces, &amp; impouerishments.</p>
                           <p>And if that the mercifull eyes, of your clement Princely nature, could but ſee the continual ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rours, the streight impriſonment, the reproach full arraynement, making no difference, in place nor time, betweene murderers, felons, &amp; rogues, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:14775:20"/>
gentlemen of all degrees, deſcended of hono<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable and worshipful parentage. Their arraigne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments being onely and directly for matters of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience, as alſo the famine, and miſerable ende of diuers impriſoned, the pittiful whippings, the pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naltie of twentie pounde a moneth, by reaſon wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of many good and worſhipful housholders, their wiues and children are brought to extreame po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uertie: Many ſtand out-lawed, and a number of poore ſoules remaine priſoners for that cauſe: beſide many other ſtrange distreſſed Catholikes, whoſe miſeries heretofore not throughly knowen to your Maiestie, haue bene and are diſgeſted with mildneſſe, and tempered with dutifulneſſe: hoping that now at length our approoued patience, will mooue your moſt tender heart, to haue ſome pitie and compaſsion of vs.</p>
                           <p>Moreouer (moste gratious dreade ſoueraigne Ladie and Queene) it may pleaſe your most excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent Maiestie, to graunt vs the grace and fauour to heare the vnfolding of our greater, and more dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerous calamitie hanging ouer our beades. For as much as nothing is more often and deepely to be called to our mindes then the frailtie of men, and howe apt and prone we are to all ſinne and wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kedneſse: for the staye and remedie whereof our Lord and Sauiour Ieſus Christ, hath instituted and left behinde him, moste holy and bleſſed ſacraments, for the comfort of mankinde, and hath commanded the vſe of them to be continued and preached in the Catholike Church, as the
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:14775:20"/>
conduits of his grace, without the which the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefits of his deare paſsion cannot ordinarily deſcende or be applyed vnto vs, as by which we are receaued, confirmed, remitted, fedde, gouerned, multiplyed and abſolutely prepared to life euerlasting.</p>
                           <p>Theſe benefites are to be valued at no leſſe price to vs, then they were to our forefathers, who religiouſly esteemed the want of them more dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerous, and diſcomfortable then death it ſelfe. The ordinary miniſters whereof are, and alwaies haue bene catholike Bishops, and Priests, lawfully called and anoynted, to that charge and ſpirituall authoritie, whom by diuine ordinance we are bound to heare, receaue and obeye, with dew honour, and reuerence, and to ſeeke vnto them as to the diſpen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſers of the myſteries of God, for counſel and helpe howe to liue and die in the loue and fauour of him, who hath power to caſt both the body and ſoule of his enemies, into perpetuall tormente of hell fyer.</p>
                           <p>In conſideration of all which neceſſary poynts, and for the humble and true purgation of our ſelues, we doe protest before the liuing God, that all and e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery Priest, or Priests, who haue at any time conuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed with vs, haue recogniſed your Maieſtie their vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doubted and lawfull Queene: <hi>Tam de iure, quam de facto.</hi> They ſpeake reuerently of you: They deuely pray for you; they zealouſly exhort your ſubiects to o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bey you; they religiouſly inſtruct vs, to ſuffer patiently what authoritie shall impoſe on vs; yet they preciſely admonish vs, that it is an hereſy condemned by
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:14775:21"/>
generall Councels, for any ſubiect to lifte vp his hand against his annoynted. This is their doctrine, this they ſpeake, this they exhorte; and if wee knowe, or shall knowe, in anie of them one poynt of treaſon, or treacherous deuiſe, or any vndecent ſpeach, or any thought iniurious to your Royall perſon: wee doe binde our ſelues by oathe irreuo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cable, to bee the first apprehenders and accuſers of ſuch.</p>
                           <p>If nowe (most Gratious Ladie) theſe Prieſtes, who haue not at any time bene detected, accu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed or charged, with anie acte, or deuiſe of trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, shall offerre to continue within this your Realme, and for ſo doing, shall be adiudged trai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tours, be it for their comming hither, or conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuance here, or for practiſing, or administring of the bleſſed Sacramentes onelye: then conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently, wee your faithfull and louing ſubiectes are like to bee capitallie touched with the ſame, treaſon: and wee knowe by no poſsible meanes, how to cleare and keepe our ſelues from it. For when the Prophets, and annoynted Prieſts of God, mooued by zeale to gayne ſoules, doe repayre he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, to distribute Spirituall comfortes, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to euerie mans neede; and comming to our gates to craue naturall ſuſtenance for their hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grie and perſecuted bodies, promiſing vs alſo ghoſtlye foode, and medecine for our vncleane ſoules: What shall wee nowe doe? we doe verily beleeue them to be Prieſtes of Gods Church, wee
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:14775:21"/>
doe certainelie knowe, that they doe daylie praye for your Maiestie. Their predeceſſoures in that calling haue ministred Baptiſme, and Confirma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion vnto your Maiestie, annoynted you Queene, and ordinarily and rightlye placed you in your Royall ſeate, as all your Maieſties anceſtours haue bene.</p>
                           <p>O poore wormes! what shall become of vs! what deſolatione are wee brought vnto! O God of Heauens, Earth and Men witneſſe with vs, and pleade our cauſe. O moste lamentable con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition, if wee receaue them, by whome we know no euill at all, it shall bee deemed Treaſon in vs: if wee doe shutte our doores and denie tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porall reliefe to our Catholique Pastours, in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpecte of their function, then are wee all, alrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die iudged most damnable Traytours to Almigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie God, and his holie members, and are moſte guiltie of that curſe, threatned to light vpon ſuch as refuſe to comfort and harbour the Apoſtles and diſciples of Christ, ſaying whoſoeuer shal not receaue you, not heare your wordes, truely it shall be eaſier for them of the lande of Sodome and Gomorra in the daye of iudgemente, &amp;c. againste which irreprooueable ſentence, wee maye in noe wyſe wraſtle.</p>
                           <p>Beholde (most gratious and Liege Soueraigne) into what streight we are plunged; be fauourable we be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeech your heighneſſe, to the liues and ſoules of men, it is the force of your Royall word, and the
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:14775:22"/>
protection of your large prerogatiue, that can onely diſperſe theſe torments, and direct vs, to the calme and ſafe hauen of indempnity of conſcience. The mindes of men, (most heigh and royall ſoueraigne, are vttered in their willes, and their willes with af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fections are commonly expreſsed in their wordes and deedes. Let our deedes throughly be examined, and there shall be found harboured, neither in our willes euill affects: neither in our mindes diſloyal thoughts. Wherefore with moſt deepe ſighes, proſtrate before the throne, and at the feete of your Heighnes royall Maiestie, we with all humilitie, doe ſubmit theſe our lamentable griefes: And albeit, that many wayes we haue bene afflicted, yet this affliction following (if it be not by the accuſtomed natural benignitie of your Maiestie ſuſpended, or taken away) will light vpon vs to our extreame ruine, and certaine calamitie, that either we (being Catholikes) muſt liue, as bodies without ſoules: or elſe looſe the temporal vſe both of body and ſoule.</p>
                           <p>O most mighty Queene, let your excellent and heauenly vertues now take their chiefe effects, let your rare and incomparable wiſdome enter into the conſideration of theſe poynts, and let that Orient pearle and gratious worke of nature, which in your royall perſon hath ſo many wealthful yeares shined amongſt vs, and adminiſtred most bright and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortable beames of grace to all men: Let this vnſpeak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able and ſingular good nature of yours, deare Ladie and Queene, delight to worke another thing like it ſelfe, or at leaſt diſlike to ſuffer a thing contrary to
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:14775:22"/>
it ſelfe. Knit the bodie and the ſoule togeather; Let not vs your catholike, natiue, english, and obedient ſubiects ſtand in more perill, for the frequenting the bleſſed Sacraments, and exerciſing the catholike re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, and that most ſecretly, then do the Catholikes ſubict to the Turke publickly: then do the peruerſe and baſphemous Iewes, haunting their Synagogues, vnder ſundry Chriſtian Kings openly: and then doe the Proteſtants enioying their publike aſſemblies vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der diuers catholike Kings and Princes quietly. Let it not be treaſon, for the ſicke man in the body, euen at the laſt gaſpe to ſeeke ghoſtly councell for the ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uation of his ſoule of a catholike Prieſt: ſo shall both ſoule and body, ſpiritual and temporal, according to our moſt bounden dutie ſerue you truely: and praye for your long and moſt proſperous raigne effectually. Then shall this your gratious tolleration ſound out your most famous memory ſo tryumphantly to all na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, that the ſame shal be preſerued of record from age to age, and conſecrated to endles glorie and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>renowne.</p>
                           <p>Accept most mercifull Prince our faithfulnes, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard our dutiful hearte: deſpiſe not our ſincere affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction. Let our rehearſed miſeries be relieued with your renowned mercies; accompt thoſe ſubiects to be vndoubtedly faithful in whoſe accuſations and liues, hath appeared a chiefe and ſpeciall care not to offend God. It nowe behoueth vs moſte humbly to craue your maiesties gratious pardon: for that we haue not obſerued the vſuall breuitie of ſupplications, being destitute of friendes to ſpeake in our behalfe; wee
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:14775:23"/>
are driuen to ſet downe ſomewhat largly by writing that which might by ſpeach with les tediouſnes bene vttered. Finally we make our hu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ble petitio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, that your excellency wil giue vs ſuch credite and affiance to our words &amp; othes, that we may fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> henceforth be dee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med cleere &amp; voy<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                                 <desc>•</desc>
                              </gap>e of al ſuſpition, both in thought, word &amp; deed: to refraine publick places of prayers, on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly for feare to fal into da<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>nable ſin, &amp; not in any hope or regard of any worldly preferme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t or policy. Seco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dly to haue that pittiful conſideration, &amp; remorſe of our calamities, as may be thought most expedient to the comfort of vs afflicted, and most agreeing with your M. moſt gratious pleaſure &amp; good likeing. Thirdly &amp; chiefly, not to ſuffer any law to be made, whereby Catholike Priests of this realme shall be banished, &amp; their receiuers highly punished. Grant, O merciful Q. that we may do the works of mercy &amp; charity to Gods Priests, ſo long as they pray for your M. &amp; vſe the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues dutifully: we are the more encouraged thus boldly to entreat with your M. becauſe in former years it hath bin deliuered in pulpets, &amp; published by books late printed, &amp; otherwiſe diuulged, that your cleme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cy neither hath, nor will punish any of your catholike ſubiects for their co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſcience, in matters of religio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> only. For our parts what ſucceſſe ſoeuer shal grow vnto vs by reaſon of this our hu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ble ſupplication, we do adui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſedly &amp; firmely vow to God, that your M. shal finde ſuch ſubects, as God requireth, and your M. deſireth. That is most louing, most loyal, and most dutiful. Our Lord God preſerue your M. to our inestimable ioye, and your endleſſe felicitie. Amen.</p>
                        </div>
                     </body>
                  </floatingText>
               </q>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb facs="tcp:14775:23"/>
               <head>The Parlaments vniust proceeding againſt Prieſtes and Catholiks, and perſecution without all cauſe by their owne iudgements.</head>
               <p>HItherto the petition of the Catholikes of England penned by the reuerend Prieſts in that time, and by their aſſent preſented to Queene Elizabeth, and to her handes deliuered by M. <hi>Shelly,</hi> in the 27. yeare of her raigne, as ſhe walked in her Parke at Greenewich, and at the time of the Parlament then holde<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, by which Parlament, all Engliſh men made Prieſts ſince the feaſt of the natiuitie of S. Iohn Baptiſt, in the firſt yeare of her raigne, were made Tray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors, and the receiuers of them fellons. The ſame M. <hi>Shelly</hi> for his preſuming to deliuer it vnto that Queene, not acquainting her priuie Councell there-with before, and for no o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther cauſe, as hee often proteſted, was by Sir Francis Walſingham then chiefe Secre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tarie, committed cloſe priſoner to the Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhallſey, where he dyed; which was the ſumme of the anſwere made vnto this moſt humble and religious petition, which notwithſtanding, that Queene and her Parlament then procee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded in making that cruell Lawe, as commonly the Proteſtants ſince haue preſumed: Although M. <hi>Robert Apreece</hi> of Waſhingly in Hunting<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tonſhire lately deceaſed, and in his life, a wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy Confeſſor, did often affirme before diuers &amp;
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:14775:24"/>
credible witneſſes, approuing it againe not three weekes before his death in the preſence of many, being thereof of purpoſe demanded, that the Earle of Kent which then was, and preſent in that Parlament, did conſtantly affirme that Queene Elizabeth did not confirme that ſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue, but ſaid <hi>I' a viſera,</hi> which diſabled it to be a lawe.</p>
               <p>He teſtified further, God is called to witnes of this true relation, that a gentlema<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> named M. <hi>Hambdon,</hi> at that time gentleman vſher of <hi>Brome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ley,</hi> then L. Chancellour, and preſent when the Queene came to allowe or diſallow the lawes, then entreated, and aſſuredly iuſtified to the ſame M. <hi>Apreece,</hi> and diuers other gentlemen aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſembled togeather at a ſupper that very daye, that this Bill was not paſſed by the Queenes conſent, but ſhe ſaid as the Earle before affir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med; and that giueth more ſtrength for this to be ſo. The ſame M. <hi>Apreece</hi> confirmed vpon his owne knowledge, that this ſtatute was not put in the written copie or Catalogue of the lawes that paſſed in that Parlament, &amp; was diuulged, and ſo continued a fourtnight together in com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon acceptance, without contradiction.</p>
               <p>But howſoeuer the trueth of this is, moſt true, and too true it was and is, that by onely pretence of ſuch a lawe, many holy and worthy Prieſtes haue bene moſt cruelly put to death, and moſt grieuous afflictions rayſed and proſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuted againſt the Catholikes of England by that
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:14775:24"/>
onely warrant. Yet this Queene ſometime be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore her death, or at leaſt ſome of her priuie Councell gaue ſome hope of a mittigation, thinking perhaps that after her death, his ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ieſtie that nowe is, being vndoubtedly by his true and moſt lawfull right to ſucceede, could no be ſo well pleaſed to finde the Catholikes of England, which had endured ſo much for their conſtant defence of the moſt vnqueſtiona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble tytle of him and his holy mother, to be ſo grieuouſly afflicted by the Proteſtants eſtate of this kingdome which had not bene ſo friendly and fauourably vnto it. Therefore ſome hopes were giuen to the Archprieſt of England then, that his Prieſtes ſhould at the laſte haue diſpu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation with their Biſhops and Doctors; and this was ſo credibly related and denounced vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to him, that two ſeuerall times he ſommoned &amp; appoynted foure of his learned Prieſts to vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>goe that combate. His aſſigned diſputants were theſe: D. <hi>VVeston.</hi> D. <hi>Smyth.</hi> D. <hi>Tho. Wright,</hi> and M. <hi>Richard Broughton.</hi> Three of theſe alſo hee appoynted to deſpute, D. <hi>Smith,</hi> M. <hi>Wright</hi> and M. <hi>Broughton</hi> at the Parlament in K. <hi>Iames</hi> his time, when the new oath was enacted, and for the fourth aſſigned Doctor <hi>Bishop.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And to confirme further this relenting diſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition in that Queene, and the wiſeſt of her counſell, beſides that which is written before, thoſe Prieſtes whom hee that writeth for the new oath vnder the name of M. <hi>Roger Widdring<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton</hi>
                  <pb n="48" facs="tcp:14775:25"/>
doeth vntruely challenge for his opinion, as both their late Apologie to the contrary, the martirdome of ſome of them for onely refuſing it (as namely M. <hi>Robert Drury</hi>) and the confeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion and acknowledgment of that author him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe vpon certaine knowledge doe teſtifie, they ſtill iuſtifie that the councell of Q. Elizabeth promiſed quietnes and tolleration, vpon Prieſts acknowledgement of temporal obedience vnto her, which none denyed: and this was the mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiue as theſe Prieſtes haue often proteſted (for I am none of them) that they were willing to yeeld ſo much as their ſpiritual bond and dutie to the See Apoſtolik which they except, would permit to Queene Elizabeth then their Soue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raigne.</p>
               <p>Neither can wee without great aſperſion of diſhonour, and all hope of all kinde of peniten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie in that princeſſe be of other minde. For ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing publickly ſo proteſted in parlament, neuer to vexe or trouble anye Romane Catholike for matter of Religion, her caſe (euen by proteſtants iudgement, not to perſecute for Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion) ſhould be too deſperate by their owne proceedings, eſpecially if we a little reflect vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that, which all the chriſtian world can witneſſe both for prieſts and Catholikes, and our prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant hiſtories themſelus thus deliuer vnto vs in theſe wordes: Elizabeth ſucceeded her ſiſter, &amp; began her raigne with ſo generall applauſe, as her ſiſter did, by reaſon the Cleargie, the No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bilitie,
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:14775:25"/>
and moſt of the commons were Romane Catholikes, who neuertheleſſe, although they knew her full determination, was to alter their ſetled courſe in Religion, yet they all with one conſent being ſet in the Parlament houſe, when the certaine newes was brought the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of Queene Maries death, they acknowledged her imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diate right, and preſently declared the ſame by diuers Proclamations, and forth-with prepared themſelues to performe their homage and feal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, which ſhee gratiouſly accepted. (<hi>Howes Historical preface in Queene Elizabeth. Stowes Historie. anno</hi> 1. <hi>Elizabeth. Cambden in apparal. Annal.</hi>)</p>
               <p>Thus theſe Proteſtant hiſtorians, and theſe renowned Biſhops, Prieſts and Catholiks were ſo far from rayſing the leaſt reſiſtance againſt her, when as we ſee they might eaſily haue kept her from being Queene, if they would haue pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeded as Proteſtants vſe to do, that thoſe holy Biſhops, as your greateſt Proteſtant antiquarie writeth (<hi>Cambden annal. pag.</hi> 27.) though they both thought Queene Elizabeth at that time to deſerue the cenſure of Excommunication, and that they had power and authoritie to inflict it on her, yet they refrayned to doe it, leaſte by that meanes the people and ſubiects of En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gland would take armes againſt her, and ſo de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe her, being by them excommunicated. And thus tender of this Queenes ſafety and quiet (though after excommunicate, and for her birth
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:14775:26"/>
by our Proteſtant hiſtorians and ſtatutes them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues not in the beſt eſtate, were all Prieſts of England, after that not onely at that time of the ſtatute againſt them, they were all moſt free and innocent, as is iuſtified in the petition before, &amp; confirmed by our Proteſtant hiſtorians, which cannot charge any one Prieſt of thoſe dayes with temporall diſobedience; but euer after continued in the ſame dutie and loyaltie, not a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny one accuſed of the contrarie, except they wil inſtance in M. <hi>Ballard,</hi> for the buſineſſe of the Queene of Scotland, and her ſonne his Maieſtie that now raigneth, and long and happely may he raigne amongſt vs, which we thinke for their dutie they owe to our Soueraigne and King <hi>Iames,</hi> Proteſtants ſhould not be haſtie to vrge: and if they ſhould, and that matter were as the Proteſtants then pretended, yet but one Prieſt in 44. yeares, ſeruing for their purpoſe, they may now acknowledge how vnequal and vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iuſt a thing it was, to condemne ſo venerable &amp; heigh a function, generally for ſo an heynous offence, when they finde none guiltie by their owne proceedings.</p>
               <p>And this innocencie of Prieſtes was that, which in thoſe latter dayes of Q. Elizabeth ſo inforced that Queene and her councel, ſo cun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ningly as they could with their politike reputa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, not to be altogether contrary to them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues, and not ingeniouſly acknowledge the wrongs and iniuries they had offered and done
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:14775:26"/>
to that ſacred vocation, to ſtay the fury, and mit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tigate the rage of their former perſecution, by occaſion whereof, and Prieſtes prooued thus innoce<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, diuers religious men, which ſpareingly before (as thoſe of the Societie) or not at all (as the Monkes of the order of S. Benedict, had vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſited England) reſorted hither in ſome numbers in thoſe latter dayes of that Queene. And thus much of the honor and loyaltie of Prieſts, and vndeniable trueth of the Religion they taught in her time.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Howe the Prieſtes and Catholikes of England, ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer deſerued the least perſecution or affliction, vnder our Soueraigne King <hi>Iames,</hi> but rather fauour, honour, and reuerence.</head>
               <p>NOW let vs come to the time of our dread leige and Soueraigne King <hi>Iames</hi>: as the world well knoweth, the affection and dutifull loue of the Prieſts and Catholikes of England toward his Maieſties right and moſt vndoubted true title to this kingdome, in the dayes of Queene Elizabeth, yet euer perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming due obedience vnto her, was not inferi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our to the beſt Proteſtants of this nation: ſo it pleaſed his Maieſtie without any exception of Prieſt or Papiſt, generally to ſpeake in publike Parlament of this whole Iland. <hi>I am the husband, and all the whole Ile is my lawful wife: I am the head, and it is my bodie: I am the Sheepheard, and it
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:14775:27"/>
is my flocke (King Iames parl. 1. ſeſſ. 1.</hi>) He therefore accounteth vs poore members of this his wife, his bodie, &amp; flocke, for being but one husband, head and ſhepheard, he hath but one wiſe, body and flocke by that relation. And at his entrance hither, by his regall teſtimonie, wee that be prieſtes and Catholikes applauded and embra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced it with as great ioy and alacritie, as thoſe that were Proteſtants, and of his Religion, as they pretende: his Maieſtie tearmeth it (<hi>ſeſs.</hi> 1. <hi>ſupr. parl.</hi> 1.) <hi>a ioy full and general applauſe, and vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>expected readines of our deſerts, memorable reſolu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, moſt wonderfull coniunction, and harmonie of our hearts, in declaring and embraceing our vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doubted King and gouernour at his firſt entrie into this kingdome, the people of all ſortes rid and ran, other flew to meete him; their eyes flaming nothing but ſparkles of affection, their mouthes and tongues vttering nothing but ſounds of ioye, their hearts, feete, and all the reſt of their members in their ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stures, diſcouering a paſsionate longing, and earne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtnes to meete and embrace, their new Soueraigne.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Thus it pleaſed him to embrace vs in gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall, as his moſt louing and dutifull ſubiects: and in particular thus he pittied our former af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flictions, and intended to mitigate and relieue them: <hi>my minde</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>was euer free from per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecution or thralling my ſubiectes in matters of conſcience. (King Iames in Parlament</hi>) therefore of himſelfe he did not thinke vs worthie to be perſecuted or inthralled, but rather light<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:14775:27"/>
of thoſe miſeries, as his next wordes a warrant: <hi>I was ſo far from encreaſing their bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dens with Roboam, as I haue ſo much, as either time occaſion, or lawe could permit, lightned them.</hi> And in his cenſure againſt <hi>Conradus Vorstius</hi> the Dutch heretike, recounting the differences betweene proteſtants and vs, hee findeth not one for which we may be perſecuted, but the contrary.</p>
               <p>At his comming in, he ſet the Catholikes and Prieſtes at libertie, gaue free pardons vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to all of them, both prieſts and others, that would ſue them foorth, and paye foure or fiue Nobles at the moſte for them to the Lorde Chancellour: In thoſe pardons, hee remitted both the guilt and danger from prieſthood, and much more then any of vs had tranſgreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed in, he ſtiled vs as our dignities, diſcentes, or callings were, gentlemen, prieſtes, or of what degree, dignitie, or preeminence ſoeuer he were, his belooued ſubiects: which wordes and ſtate are incompatible wtth the name of Treaſon: in thoſe pardons hee pardoned whatſoeuer could be in any rigour interpreted to be within the daunger of that Lawe, both our comming into England, and abyding and remayninge heere: ſo that by pardon being dead, they can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not poſſiblie be reuiued, becauſe the graunt is irreuocable. Our comming in, was but one indiuiall acte and offence in Lawe, and ſo re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted, cannot be offence: our continuance,
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:14775:28"/>
and remayning ſo long as we doe not reiterate it againe, by going foorth, and comming in the ſecond time, is alſo but one particular, ſingular, and indiuidual action, without diſcontinuance, one <hi>ens fluens,</hi> as all ſuch not interrupted be: an hower, a daye, a weeke, a moneth, a yeare, a life, an age, and the like. This all philoſophie, &amp; common reaſon (whereon our common law is, and muſt be founded) teacheth vs. Thus diuers proteſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, &amp; good lawyers haue anſwered: thus his Maieſtie eſteemed, when hearing of a prieſt named M. <hi>Freeman,</hi> put to death for his prieſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood, by the Iudges of Warwicke, ſoone after his Maieſties comming hither, with ſigne of ſorrow anſwered: <hi>Alas poore man, had he not foure nobles to buye his pardon</hi>: by which he conclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, that a prieſt being pardoned for his prieſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood, could not after for being a prieſt be put to death, or tearmed a traytour, or indanger his friends and receauers, but was a free and lawfull true ſubiect, from that imputation. His Maieſtie alſo allowed the times of Conſtantine for times of true Religion, and the Roman Church then, and after, to be the true, &amp; our mother Church, and not to be departed from.</p>
               <p>Then wee may not ſo vnder-value the lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning and iudgement of our learned and Soue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raigne in diuinitie, and hiſtories, but he well knoweth (which no learned man is ignorant of) that in the time of Conſtantine, the Church of Rome had the ſame holy ſacrifice of Maſſe,
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:14775:28"/>
and the ſame holy ſacrifycing prieſthood, which now it hath, which I will hereafter demon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrate by the beſt learned proteſtant antiquaries of this nation, as alſo that the Church of Rome at the reuolt of King Henry the 8. was the ſame in all eſſential things, which it was in that pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fixed time of Conſtantine; And to be liberal to my needy proteſtant contrymen in this caſe, I ſay, that the Church of Rome, &amp; the Religion of the Prieſts of England, their prieſthood, and ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifice of the Maſſe, is the ſame which were in Rome, and in this Iland alſo in S. Peters time, &amp; in euery age without interruption ſince then, vnto theſe dayes of Proteſtants. And if we may beleeue <hi>Iſaac Caſaubon,</hi> the ſtipendarie cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pion for the Proteſtants of England, who ſaith, <hi>ab ore regis accepi,</hi> and <hi>haec est Religio Regis An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gliae, &amp;c. (Iſaac Caſaubon contra Cardinal Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ron. Pag. 50.51.52.) I haue it from the Kings mouth, this is the Religion of the King, this is the Religion of the Church of England: The fathers of the Prima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiue church did acknowledge one ſacrifice in chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Religion, that ſucceeded in the place of the ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifice of Moſes. The ſacrifice offered by Priests, is Christs bodie and the ſame obiect, and thing, which the Romane Church beleeueth.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Theſe and ſuch things troubled the heads of ſome great Proteſtant perſecutors in England, (their conſciences being guiltie of ſome-what not good) that they coulde not enduer the leaſt clemency of his Maieſtie towards his loy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:14775:29"/>
and trueſt catholike ſubiects, but olde ſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tagems and tragedies of Queene Elizabeths time, muſt needes be renewed and playde a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine, to bring not only the Catholikes of En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gland, but their holy religion (if poſſiblie it could be done) into obloquie, eſpeciallie with his gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious Maieſtie: and thereupon an execrable and moſt damnable treacherie by gunpowder was to be inuented, for a few wicked &amp; deſperatly minded men to doe, whom many proteſtants tearmed papiſts; although the true Prieſts and Catholikes of England knew them not to bee ſuch, nor can any proteſtant truely ſay, that any one of them was ſuch a one, as their lawes and proceedings againſt vs, name Papiſts, Popiſh recuſants, or the like. What he was, papiſt or proteſtant, rich or poore, noble or vnnoble, of Courte or countrey, that was inuentor of this horrible deuiſe, I will not diſcuſſe, but referre all indifferently minded men, and of iudgement able to diſcerne the probable trueth in ſuch a cauſe, to the hiſtorie and circumſtances thereof, as they are ſet downe by the Proteſtant hiſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rian, M. Ed. Hows (<hi>hiſtor. of Engl. in King Iames.</hi>)</p>
               <p>But to graunt to our Proteſtant perſecutors, for arguments ſake (that which I may not) and they will as hardly proue, that this wicked in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpriſe was firſt inuented by <hi>Catesby,</hi> and ſome of his conſorts, and that diuers of them were papiſts, and had acquaintance with the chiefe Ieſuite then in England, who at leaſt in confeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:14775:29"/>
knew of this conſpiracie, &amp; did not reueale it: that there were foure of this co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>panie arraig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned for the conſpiracie, three gentleme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> (though two of theſe, <hi>Fauxe</hi> and <hi>Keyes</hi> were but ſeruing men) as the fourth, <hi>Thomas Bates</hi> ſtyled yeoma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. that one Knight and three Eſquires concealed it, of which the Knight was ſo ignorant, that as the Proteſtant relator of this matter ſaith, at his death he ſpake theſe wordes (<hi>Howes ſupr. in Sir Edward Digby) If he had knowne it first to haue bene ſo fowle a treaſon, he would not haue concea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led it, to haue gayned a world:</hi> Which he could not haue truely ſaid, if he had knowne it in par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular, &amp; in it ſelfe a moſt horrible damnable thing; and the reſt as this author writeth, dyed penitent; <hi>and beſought all Catholikes, neuer to attempt ſuch a bloodie acte, being a courſe which God did neuer fauour nor proſper.</hi> Thoſe that were vp in tumult with Catesby, <hi>were</hi> (as the Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtants relateth <hi>(Howes ſupr.) neuer full fourſcore ſtrong, beſides many of their houshold ſeruants (no doubt papiſts if their maisters were ſo) forſooke them how erlie: yet they diuulged many deteſtable vntruths against the king &amp; state, omitting no ſcandal which they thought might ſerue their traiterous purpoſe, &amp; that they were aſſembled and prepared to ſome ſpecial ſeruice, for the aduancement of the catholike cauſe, hoping thereby to haue drawne into their rebellion, thoſe of that religion, &amp; other wilful malecontents</hi>:</p>
               <p>And to make euident, it was rather a madde deſperat attempt of one priuate kindred, or
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:14775:30"/>
acquaintance, then of any religion. Thus it is creedibly recounted by them that knew their diſcents (for I was a ſtranger to them all) <hi>Catesby</hi> and <hi>Tresham</hi> were ſiſters children; the two <hi>Graunts</hi> brethren, and the elder intermarryed with <hi>Winters</hi> ſiſter, calling his eldeſt ſonne <hi>Win<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter Graunt</hi>: the <hi>Winters</hi> Grandmother, was ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter to the Gra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dmother of <hi>Catesby</hi> &amp; <hi>Treshame,</hi> and ſo they were kinſmen. <hi>Yorke,</hi> and the <hi>Win<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters</hi> ſiſters children, by the <hi>Englebies</hi>: the two <hi>Wrytes</hi> long time dependers of <hi>Catesby,</hi> and their ſiſter married to <hi>Percy: Catesby, Tresham, T. Winter,</hi> two <hi>Wrights</hi> and <hi>Graunt</hi> were in Eſſex rebellion. All theſe were yong except <hi>Percy,</hi> who gaue the Piſtoll to his Maiſter the olde Earle of Northumberland in the Tower: And if any of theſe were Catholikes, or ſo dyed, they were knowne Proteſtants not long before, and neuer frequenters of Catholike Sacramentes with any Prieſt as I could euer learne: &amp; as all the Proteſtant courts will witneſſe, not one of them a conuicted or knowne Catholike or re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſant. And of all theſe remembred of that con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiracie or acquainted with it, the L. <hi>Mounteagle,</hi> now <hi>L. Morley,</hi> who diſcloſed it, was moſt no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to be a Catholike, as his Ladie and Childre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> were.</p>
               <p>Therefore ſeeing (as the Proteſtants haue te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtified) no Catholikes could by any deuiſe, be drawne into this matter, not one among ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny hundreth, or thouſands of knowne Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>likes
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:14775:30"/>
priuie vnto it, but deteſting it when it was knowne, the <hi>Archpriest</hi> by writing condemning it preſently when he vnderſtood it, all his <hi>Priests</hi> abhorring it, &amp; euery one of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> with the <hi>Arch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priests</hi> warrant, and the conſent of the chiefeſt Catholikes in England, and all they in their pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titions hereafter condemning it for a moſt hor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rible offence (<hi>Archpriest letter of prohibit. Author of moderat anſw. epiſt. dedicat. to the king. Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liks petitions to the parlament and chiefe Secretary</hi>) And not one either Prieſte or knowne Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like, with all thoſe ſtrickt and diligent ſearches and examinations then made by the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtant ſtate about it, was either prooued, or pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bablie ſuſpected to be guiltie of it: but ſo farre freede, that the Lords of the Councel, requeſted that a Prieſt ſhould be appoynted to perſwade and aſſure <hi>Fauxe</hi> (a chiefe agent in it) that he was bound in conſcience to vtter what he could of that conſpiracie, and M. Tho. Write a learned Prieſt did hereupon come to the councell, and offer his beſt ſeruice herein, and had a warrant to that purpoſe ſubſigned with 12. priuie Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellors hands, which he ſhewed vnto me, and I am witneſſe of his hauing ſuch a warrant. But as he ſaid, <hi>Fauxe</hi> had confeſſed all they could wiſh before he could come vnto him, ſo that no man of conſcience can, or will thinke, but gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally al the Prieſtes and Catholikes of England did rather deſerue fauour, honour, and enfran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiſement, from all afflictions, for their moſte
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:14775:31"/>
religious, and holy ſeruing of God, and as loyal obedient and dutiful trueth, alleageance and fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>delitie to our proteſtant King and countrey, then the leaſt disfauour for this practiſe.</p>
               <p>For if the Prieſtes and Catholikes ſo manie thouſands in England would haue entertayned it, no man can be ſo malicious, and ſimple to thinke, but there would haue bene a greater aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſemblie then foureſcore, to take ſuch an action in hand; and the councell could not be ſo win<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king eyed, but they would haue found foorth ſome one or other culpable, which they could neuer doe, though ſome of them moſt powrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble in it, tentered and racked forth their enuie and hatred againſt vs, to the vttermoſt limites they could extend. To confirme this our inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cencie, the kings Maieſtie in his ſecond procla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation againſt that wickedneſſe, calleth all the <hi>confederates, men of lewde inſolent diſpoſition, and for the moſt part of deſperate eſtate (Proclamat. 2. againſt Percy, &amp;c. an.</hi> 1605.) and in his third Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clamation, when they were all diſcouered and knowne, thus he proclaimeth and publiſheth: <hi>(Procl. 3. an. eod. 1605.) It appeareth now in part who were the complices in this deteſtable Treaſon, publi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shed by our former proclamations, in their aſſembling together, to mooue our people to rebellion, although perhaps many of them did neuer vnderstande the ſecrete of his (Percies) abhominable purpoſe.</hi> Where wee plainely ſee, that the King and his coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſell then knew the complices, and partakers of
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:14775:31"/>
that villanie, yet they neuer taxed any Prieſt, or knowne catholike therewith.</p>
               <p>And it further proueth, that they which ioy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned therein knew not the practiſe in particular, neither durſt the workers of it diſcloſe it to the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, leaſt for the vilenes of it, they would haue reie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted or reuealed it, as al true Catholiks would haue done. And his Maieſtie in publicke parla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, doth free Catholikes as much as Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtants in this inuention, when hee plainelie ſaith (as trueth is) if it had taken effect, <hi>Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtants and Papists should haue all gone awaye, and perished together (Kings ſpeath parl. an.</hi> 1605.) And to demonſtrate from his maieſties publike acte, that Prieſtes and catholikes were as inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent as Proteſtants, and as the Kings Maieſtie himſelfe, of this, and all ſuch vileneſſe, hee declareth by Proclamation (<hi>Proclamat. die 7. No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uembr. an.</hi> 1605) <hi>We are by good experience ſo well perſwaded, of the loyaltie of diuers ſubiectes (of the Romane religion) that they doe as much abhorre this detestable conſpiracie, as our ſelfe, and will be rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die to doe their beſt endeauours, though with ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pence of their blood, to ſuppreſse al attempters againſt our ſafetie, and the quiet of our eſtate, &amp; to diſcouer whomſoeuer they shall ſuſpect to be of rebellious or trayterous diſpoſition.</hi> Thus his maieſtie by good experience hath publickly pronounced.</p>
               <p>And though I am no Ieſuit, yet religio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, iuſtice &amp; charitie draw my pen to write thus much, for the ſuppoſed guiltines of <hi>M. Garnet,</hi> ſuperior of
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:14775:32"/>
Ieſuits here at that time, we haue but the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtants affirmation, and him denying it, and we haue from the ſame proteſtants, that which ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther iuſtifyeth his denial, then their affirmatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: for they publiſhed his examination before the Councell, wherein they ſet downe his opinion (<hi>H. Garnets examination before the Councel. anno</hi> 1605.) <hi>That the Pope could not depoſe the king,</hi> and they adde his reaſon thus; <hi>becauſe the King was neuer ſubiect to the Pope</hi>; which reaſon I doe not examine, but thus iuſtifie, that if in his opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, the pope could not depoſe the king; and the king was neuer ſubiect to the pope, then the pope could not licence any man, ſuppoſed a Catholike, ſo to proceed; for himſelfe could not by this his opinion ſo doe, much leſſe any papiſt by his allowance: and if the king was neuer ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iect to the pope, he could neuer be ſubiect to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny papiſt, the popes and his owne ſubiect. And whereas the proteſtants condemne ſome other Ieſuits for this matter, and among them Father <hi>Baldwyne,</hi> yet hauing him priſoner diuers years, vnder their ſtricteſt examination, they at laſt diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſed him as innocent and guiltleſſe therein, &amp; that with honour. And how-ſo-euer the caſe ſtood with the accuſed Ieſuites, we are euide<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tly taught by theſe greateſt authorities, that both prieſts and catholikes were vpon this pretence moſt vniuſtly perſecuted; although beſides all theſe reaſons, wee by publicke conſent both of <hi>Archpriest,</hi> beſt learned cleargie and Catholikes,
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:14775:32"/>
preſented and offered to maintaine our cauſe &amp; innocencie in theſe humble petitions: and firſt to his maieſtie in this maner.</p>
               <q>
                  <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                     <body>
                        <div type="petition">
                           <head>
                              <hi>TO THE MOST EXCEL<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>CELLENT and mightie Prince, our gratious</hi> and dread Soueraigne, IAMES by the grace of God, King of great Britaine, France and Ireland, in the yeare 1605. iuſtifying the Innocencie of Catholikes, and trueth of their holie Religion, againſt all beſt learned prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant aduerſaries.</head>
                           <opener>
                              <salute>Moſt gratious Soueraigne.</salute>
                           </opener>
                           <p>THe late intended conſpiracie against the life of your royall maieſtie (the life, vnion, rule, and direction to theſe vnited kingdomes) was ſo heynous an impietie, that nothing which is holy, can make it legittimate, no pretence of Religion can be alleaged to excuſe it, God and heauen condemne it, men and earth detest it, innocents bewaile it, the nocent and vnhappie delinquents themſelues in repentance haue lamented it, and your dutiful, religious and learned Catholikes, Priests and others, which haue endu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red most for their profeſsion, holde it in greateſt horror, and will ſweare, protest, promiſe and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forme to your Maiestie, whatſoeuer loyaltie, obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence and dutie, is due from a ſubiect to his tempo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall prince, by the word of God, lawe of nature, or hath bene vſed by the ſubiects of this kingdome,
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:14775:33"/>
to any your chriſtian progenitors from the first to the laſt: acknowledge and render to your honorable counſel, and all magiſtrates in ciuill cauſes, ſo much honor, reuerence and ſubmiſsion, and to all other proteſtant ſubiects, like amitie and neighbourly affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, as if they were of the ſame Religion, which we profeſſe.</p>
                           <p>Yet, this is the miſerable and diſtreſſed state, of many thouſands your moſt loyall and louing ſubiectes (dread liege) for their faithful dutie to God, and a Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion taught in this kingdome, and embraced by all your progenitors, and our ancestors, ſo many hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred yeares; that euery aduerſary may preach, &amp; print againſt vs, and make their challenge, as though ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther for ignorance we could not, or for distruſt of our cauſe, wee were vnwilling to make them anſwere, or come to triall: when quite contrarie, we haue often, earnestly, and by all meanes we could, deſired to haue it granted, with equal conditions, against the most ſelected, and beſt learned doctors of that Religion.</p>
                           <p>And at this preſent, when your chiefest Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant Clergie, Bishops and others is aſſembled, wee most humblie intreate, this ſo reaſonable a placet, that although they will not (as we feare) euer con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent to an indifferent choyce, oppoſition, and defence in questions: yet at the leaſt, to auoyde the wonder of the world, they will be content, that we may haue publike audience of thoſe articles, opinions and pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſe, for which we are ſo much condemned and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecuted. If we shall not be able to defend or proue a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny poſition generally maintained in our doctrine, to
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:14775:33"/>
be conformeable to thoſe rules in diuinitie, which your Maiestie and the protestant lawes of England (we can profer no more) haue confirmed for holie, the canonicall ſcriptures, the firſt generall councels, the dayes of Conſtantine, and the primatiue Church, let the penalties be impoſed and executed against vs. If we performe it, or this petition may not be admit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, we trust, that both our office to God, and dutie to our Prince, is diſcharged in this poynt.</p>
                           <p>Your royall perſon, and that honorable Conſistory now aſſembled, are holden in your doctrine, to be ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preame ſentencer, euen in ſpiritual buſines in this kingdome; we therefore hope, you wil not in a Courte from whence no appeale is allowed, and in matters of ſuch conſequence, proceede to iudgement, or deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine of execution, before the arraigned is ſummo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned to anſwere, hath receaued or refuſed trial, is, or can be prooued guiltie. If we be condemned, and our cauſe be iust, and religion true; it is God, &amp; not man, againſt whom you proceede in ſentence. If our profeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion be erroneous, and yet for conſent with ſo manie nations, and ſo long continuance, it is leſſe vnpuni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shed: you onely pardon the frailtie and ignorance of earthly men, and fight not with the heauenly. Denie not that to vs (your euer true and obedient ſubiects) in a religion ſo auntient, which your collegued prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, the King of Spaine, and the Archduke, do offer to the ſo many yeares diſobedient Netherlandes, vpon their temporall ſubmittance, in ſo late an embraced doctrine: that which the Arrian Emperours of the Eaſte, permitted to the Catholikes (Bishops, prieſtes,
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:14775:34"/>
Churches) tolleration: what the barbarian Vandals often offered, and ſometimes truely performed in A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fricke: What the Turkish Emperour in Greece, and Protestant Princes in Germanie, and other places, conformable to the examples of Protestant rulers, not vnanſwerable to your owne princely pietie, pit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, and promiſe, no deguſt to any equally minded Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtant or Puritane at home, a iub<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                                 <desc>•</desc>
                              </gap>ly to vs diſtreſſed, a warrant of ſecuritie to your Maiestie in all opinions, from all terrours and dangers. From which of what kinde ſoeuer, we most humblie beſeech the infinite mercie of Almightie God to preſerue your Heighnes, and ſend you, your Queene and posteritie, all happie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe and felicitie, both in heauen and earth, Amen.</p>
                        </div>
                        <div type="petition">
                           <head>Another petition of the Catholiks of England to his Maieſtie, at the ſame time.</head>
                           <p>REmember moſt worthie Prince, not onely howe grieuous, but how general the penalties against your catholikes be enacted; and yet new threatnings be made, that new &amp; more ſtrange (as <hi>nec inter ge<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                                 <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes</hi>) shall be ordeyned: The bodies, honors, reputati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons and ritches of the husbands, to be punished for their wiues religion and ſoules, to which they are neither husba<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ds nor ſuperiours; children to be taken fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> their parents, &amp; parents to be depriued of their e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ducation, which Catholike princes doe not, and in conſcience cannot offer to Iewes themſelues, though (in ſome opinions) the ſlaues of Chriſtians. Children, ſeruants, kinſmen and neighbours to be made hired
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:14775:34"/>
eſpials, to betray their parents, maisters, kindred, in things as vnlawful, which the whole catholik world honoreth for holie. Commendable arts, functions of phyſicke, and which haue no connexion with reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, to be put to ſilence in catholikes. The ſeuere pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naltie (twentie pounde a moneth) for not monethly profeſsing the protestant faith in churches (when in all diuinitie the precept of profeſsion of true and vndoubted faith, <hi>in ſe</hi> &amp; <hi>ex ſe,</hi> bindeth but ſeldome) is to be encreaſed. And others of ſuch condition, too many here to be mentioned, and too grieuous and vnnatural: we hope, in your princely opinion, to be concluded by a kings conſent vnder fauour, for all, wee instance in one most heauie, and generall in thoſe of our deceaſed Queene. All Priestes, though neuer ſo dutiful or obedient, be cenſured for traytours, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>qually with the greatest offendor, in the ſinne of treaſon, when many guiltleſſe ſoules of that ſacred order, would not for thouſands of worldes once con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent to any ſuch, or far inferiour offence. A thing moſt strange, and beyond all example, that men in reſpect onely of their calling and function, and that function ſo reuerenced by all our forefathers, should without further cauſe be condemned, as guiltie of ſo detestable a crime.</p>
                           <p>We defende holy Priesthood to be a Sacrament, which being ordained by God, cannot be changed by man, Pope, Prelate, or humane power, but remaining in all things, ſubſtance and doctrine, the ſame, which in thoſe daies when it was ſo honorably eſteemed of all your Christian progenitors, and when our mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:14775:35"/>
church kept her first integritie by your heigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe iudgement, as we are reddie to make defence. It is the honour of our King in heauen (most migh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie Soueraigne) for which we continue in combate: that religion which the whole catholike world in all generall councels, popes, doctors, and learned men, haue euer profeſſed; wherein this nation (as our Protestants acknowledge) was conuerted, all our Christian ancestry embraced, and which all princes in the ſchoole of Christ (of whom your Maieſtie is de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcended) mayntained in the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues &amp; in their ſubiects. That which is ſo general, ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>not be ſurre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dred by a ſmal number, of one kingdome: It is not in the power of man, to reſigne the honour of God: if it will pleaſe your Maieſtie to vouchſafe vs licence to request, and grace to obtaine, that your owne princely ſentence &amp; cenſure may stande, that wee ought not to departe <hi>further from the Romane Church, our mother Church</hi> (by your iudgement) <hi>than ſhee is departed from her ſelfe, when ſhe was in her beſt, and floriſhing ſtate</hi>: And that the time of Constantine was incorrupted in religion, wee humbly againe offer tryal before your heigneſſe, with equall conditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of ſchooles, against the most ſelected and choſen protestant Bishops and doctors of your dominions, to prooue or defend any, or euery ſubstantial article, which wee now profeſſe, to be agreeable vnto (and not, diſſenting) the knowne publike Catholike doctrine of that mother Church, in thoſe your mentioned incorrupted dayes of Chriſtianitie.</p>
                           <p>And ſeeing the disfauour and penalties against
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:14775:35"/>
laye Catholikes, are grounded vpon their recuſan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie, to be preſent at your protestant ſeruice: wee humblie beſeech, it may be called to memorie, howe they haue protested in ſeuerall ſupplicati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, one to your Maiestie, before the ende of the laste parlament: and the other to Queene Eliza<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beth, in the twentie ſeuenth yeare of her raigne, to be builded onely vpon feare of offending God. To which their ſo long and manifolde diſgraces, loſſes, impriſonments, and ſufferings, are ſufficient witneſſe: And for further triall thereof, haue of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered to repayre to your Proteſtant Churches, and ſeruice, without further exception, if the learned of your Religion can, and doe prooue to the lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned of their profeſsion, that it may be performed without offence to God, which is ſo much in the opinion of all diuines, as any Chriſtian ſubiects can offer in this caſe.</p>
                           <p>Th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                                 <desc>•</desc>
                              </gap>s if your Protestant Cleargie doe refuſe, or doe not ſatisfie ſo Christian a requeſt, we hope your Maiestie beeing wiſe, learned, iuditious, and gratious, will perceaue, that the ſeueritie of the lawes against them, for that cauſe, is not to be put in practiſe. Theſe things in moſt hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble manner, wee commende to your heighest and mercifull conſideration: And ſo deſiring of the Almightie, to graunt all happineſſe and proſperitie to your Maieſtie, and poſteritie: wee conclude in all dutifull ſubiection, with that auntient Father <hi>(Tertullian in Apollget.) Wee will faithfully ſerue you in your Pallace, we will accompanie
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:14775:36"/>
other your ſubiects in the market, wee will ioyne with them in the fielde, againſt your ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies, onely to you we leaue the Churches.</hi>
                           </p>
                        </div>
                     </body>
                  </floatingText>
               </q>
               <p>Theſe two petitions were printed and preſented to his Maieſtie in the Parlament, when the new oath was enacted, and the foure remembred Prieſts appointed by the Arch-prieſt then to performe that chal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lenge or petition; likewiſe at the ſame time was preſented to the Parlament, by the handes of Sir <hi>Francis Hastings,</hi> and Sir <hi>Richard Knightly,</hi> two Puritanes of that Parlament, from the chiefe Catholikes of England, with the allowance of the Arch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prieſt, and his cleargie; this petition fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing to the ſame purpoſe.</p>
               <q>
                  <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                     <body>
                        <div type="petition">
                           <pb n="71" facs="tcp:14775:36"/>
                           <head>The humble petition of the chiefe Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like Recuſants of England, preſented to the heigh Court of Parlament, in the yeare 1605. by the handes of Sir <hi>Francis Hastings,</hi> and Sir <hi>Richard Knightly,</hi> then of that houſe of Parlament: to both which it was deliuered, by the ſaid Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholikes.</head>
                           <p>THe proceedings of that heigh Court of Parlament, in the daies of our late Queene Elzabeth, againſt the Catholike ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iects of this kingdome, were for ſeueritie far beyond example; which they hoped for manie most iust, reaſonable true cauſes, &amp; were to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceaue their ende, when shee should ceaſe to liue, and by death, determine her perſonall quarrells and contentions against the Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and Apostolike power of the Sea of Rome. Eſpecially by the ioyful and happie entrance &amp; Coronation of our moſt honoured King Iames, moſt free from thoſe tearmes wherewith she was intangled, at temporall peace, amitie, and vnitie with that holy Sea, with the ſacred Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pyre, all Chriſtian Kings and Princes, by vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doubted royal diſcent, the most lawful, legiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mate,
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:14775:37"/>
and rightful King of all theſe his vni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted kingdomes. Wee that be Catholiques in England, and had euer bene ſo true and faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full to the onely vnited true title of him and his bleſsed Mother, and neuer entred into any diſſotiation against it, aſſuredly hoped, hee would not ſingularlie drawe his ſword of per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecution against vs, his most dutiful, faithful, and obedient ſubiects, in whom he could finde nothing to reuenge or punish: for he publickly proteſted in that Court of Parlament: <hi>his mind was euer free from perſecution or enthral<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling his ſubiects in matters of conſcience,</hi> and the burthens of Catholikes were rather to be lightned, then with Roboam to be en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſed <hi>(king Iames ſpeach in parlament. 1. ſeſſ. 1.)</hi>
                           </p>
                           <p>But ſeeing all this notwithstanding, your Parlament now aſſembled (contrary to our hopes, and otherwiſe our deſeruings, as wee hope haue bene) doth rather preſage an inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded increaſe, then either ceaſing, or mittiga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of theſe our miſeries, and extreame affli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions: we feare leaſt ſilence in vs might be ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken as an interpretatiue yeelding or conſente, that we are not altogether vnworthely af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flicted, with ſo strange calamities: for the
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:14775:37"/>
world cannot otherwiſe in wiſdome cenſure, that ſuch punishment by ſo heigh a iudgeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t should be impoſed vpon men (ſubiects, friends, and kinſmen, ſo generally) except guiltie of ſome most heinous, or execrable fact or offence againſt God, our King and countrey. Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore you must giue vs leaue in this perplexed caſe, to contest against you in the humbleſt &amp; best maner we may, and leaue it a memoriall to potesteritie, that if you perſiſt or proceede in perſecution, vve proteſt before God, and in our conſciences, vve shal be vniustly perſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted. If you vvill continue or encreaſe perſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, you muſt pretend ſome motiue to doe it, and if you deſire to cloath or shaddow it, vvith any cloake or colour of iustice, it muſt be foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded vpon ſome probable conuiction, if our gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall deſeruing ſuch punishments to be ſo gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally proſecuted againſt vs, vvhich muſt needs be ſome vniuerſal diſobedience, or diſloyaltie in vs all, either temporall to our terreſtrial king and contrey on earth, or ſpirituall to God and the heauenly kingdome; vve know no thirde to vvhom your Religion vvould vvish vs to performe obedience.</p>
                           <p>For our diſcharge to the first, vve haue ſerued now vnder your vigilant, and ſuruey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:14775:38"/>
eyes, diuers apprentiships in continuall perſecution; yet from the first beginning there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, vnto this day, you haue not found by all thoſe narrow ſearches, and ſcrutinies you haue made, that vve (whom you thus perſecute vnder the name of Religion) haue bene thus founde diſloyal to our temporal prince, neither is that pretended in any of your laws againſt vs. And in this late vngratious and hellish conſpiracie, if they had bene ſuch as your lawes and proceedings ſtile Papiſts and Recuſants, yet his Maiestie by his publike proclamation <hi>(King Iames Proclamation in Septemb. an. 1605)</hi> giueth that testimony of the loyal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, and loue of his Catholike ſubiects vnto him, that you vvhich perſecute vs doe not, &amp; by his regal vvordes cannot accuſe vs there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in. And the number of theſe certainely knowe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> conuicted Catholques, vvhich you perſecute for religion, and both by his maiesties declara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and all proteſtant most diligent ſearches and examinations, thus innocent, and vvhich detest all diſloialtie, are <hi>500.</hi> to one of thoſe vvhich you prooue guiltie, by your publike Courts and recordes. Neither can you finde by anie ſuch proceedings against Catholiques, that theſe malefactours vvere of the number
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:14775:38"/>
of thoſe vvhich you haue ſo punished and perſecuted for our religion. The Archprieſt of England, and the reuerend prieſts of his com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panie (vvho best knew vvho be Catholiques by their frequenting holie Sacraments) haue by publike vvritings vtterlie renounced the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, and condemned their lewed enterpriſe, for most vvicked impietie.</p>
                           <p>Therefore in conſcience and iustice you can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not vpon this pretence, rayſe a generall perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cution against vs: for in ſo doing, you should vniustlie perſecute thouſa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ds of thoſe that be as innocent, as your ſelues can be, or his Maiestie himſelfe by his owne testimony of vs <hi>(King Iam procl. ſupr. an. 1605.) Wee are by good experience ſo well perſwaded of their loy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>alties, that they doe as much abhorre this deteſtable conſpiracie as our ſelfe, and will be reddie to doe their beſte endeuours, though with expence of their blood to ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſe all attempts againſt our ſafetie, and the quiet of our ſtate, &amp; to diſcouer whom ſoeuer they ſhall ſuſpect to be of rebellious or trayterous diſpoſition.</hi> This is his Maie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sties ſentence by good experience of vs his catholique ſubiects, your petitioners. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore vve are confident, vve rather deſerue fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fauour
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:14775:39"/>
then affliction at your Court. And yet if contrary to the lavves of this Kingdome, you vvould ſay, that the lands, goods, and liues of delinquents (vvhich vve doe not thinke you intende, or vve vvill vviſh you to ſpare in theſe offendours) doe not ſatisfie in ſuch caſes, you must notvvithſtanding (to conteine your proceedings vvithin the ſhaddowe of iuſtice) not impoſe the offence and puniſhment of the guiltie, vpon thoſe that be ſo innocent: The highest law and rule enacteth: <hi>anima quae peccauerit, ipſa morietur</hi>: and as a great Counſellour and ſecretarie of estate hath now publiſhed in print for your direction <hi>(ſolum ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cis artifices arte perire ſua (Rob. Earle of Salisb. in his booke an. 1605.)</hi> Therefore wee stand ſo cleare in your owne knowledges and co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſciences fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> all temporal diſobedience, that in rigour of iuſtice, it taketh from you all cauſe, and pretence, vvhy theſe or any afflictions at all, ſhould be impoſed vpon vs, in thoſe re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpects.</p>
                           <p>Then you must directlie make your quarrel to perſecute for religion, or recuſancie, a depen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dancie thereof: If Religion bee obiected, vvee anſwere as vvee haue euer done, and deſire no further fauour for our Religion (in
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:14775:39"/>
your ovvne knowledge here ſo antient) then yow obteyned of vs for your owne ſo new, that the examples of Queene <hi>Marie</hi> her time, (which many of your profeſsio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> accompt notwith<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſtanding tyrannicall) may be followed. Let a co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>petent number of our learned prieſts, be cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led to any of your vniuerſities, or other publick place, vvhere the beſt learned of your religion ſhal giue them meeting: let ſuch questions and propoſitions as concerne the eſpeciall points in controuerſie be propoſed, ſufficient time of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſideration allowed, and other ſuch equal condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions granted, as were to your chiefest Biſhops and doctors, in the mentioned time. And if our catholique diſputation ſhal not be able to iustifie and maintaine our religion and cauſe to be ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, you may at your pleaſure proceede against vs, if we perſist therein. You haue long time, and with grieuous puniſhments perſecuted vs, yet you would neuer vouchſafe vs ſo meane a trial and iuſtice in this kinde: Execution (as you know) before conuiction is preposterous and cruel iniustice, &amp; both by your Biſhops and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ieſties cenſure in publick, <hi>Correction without inſtructio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> is but tyranny. (D.</hi> Matthew <hi>now proteſt. Archb. of Yorke, Serm. before the K. and parl. K. Iames ſpeach in parlament.</hi>
                           </p>
                           <p>
                              <pb n="78" facs="tcp:14775:40"/>If our Recuſancie, or refuſall to be preſent at your new church-ſeruice, is alledged a pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence against vs, being a practicall acte and profeſsion of religion, it dependeth vpon the former queſtion, concerning religion: for nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther catholiques nor proteſtants do teach, that men ſo far differing therein as we and you, can in conſcience communicate together in ſuch things. And no enemie or perſecutor of vs can imagine, or inuent any allegation for this our refuſall, but either obstinacie in our willes, or ignorance in our vnderſtandings: <hi>non datur medium:</hi> we cannot conceaue what you can o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe deuiſe. Our impriſonme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts, loſſes, diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>graces, and ſeuerest puniſhments in ſo manie yeares, being the whole life of a man, from time of diſcretion) the knowne bridles of obsti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate people) will condemne all men of too much will, and little iudgement, that could charge vs with this former. That which wee haue offered in religion, freeth vs in the ſecond, and condemneth our accuſers.</p>
                           <p>And to manifeſt nowe, (as often wee haue done before) that we are neither carryed away by wilfulneſſe or ignorance in this debate, wee haue at ſundry times by moſt earnest ſuites &amp; petitions deſired and offered and still doe, that
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:14775:40"/>
if your best learned Protestant Biſhops and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uines can, and ſhall proue vnto the learned of our ſide, that we may repayre vnto your chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches, and there be preſent at your ſeruice, without moſt grieuous offence to God, we vvil vvillingly performe it. Wherefore vee hope that you vvho in your owne profeſsion vvould bee esteemed zealous and religious, vvil iudge this our offer to be ſuch, that no Christians can offer more: And conſequently further re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flect and conſider hovv diſhonorable, ſhameful, and ſinfull it vvould be to your Conſistorie, &amp; vvhole Religion, to impoſe and multiplie pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nalties vpon vs (theſe offers conſidered) for not doing thoſe things, vvhich by your ovvne knovvledge, your beſt learned in diuinitie, on vvhoſe vvordes and vvarrant you hazard your ſoules, cannot, nor vvill not, take vpon them, to maintaine, as lavvfull for vs to doe.</p>
                           <p>But if ſo many ſuites, ſupplications, reaſons, and examples vvill not call you to a contrary minde, but you haue ſet vp your reſolution, vvithout any anſvvere or defence by vs, to be our accuſers, iudges, and executioners, and ſingularly vvithout any example at all, in the vvorld, either of Chriſtians, or others,
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:14775:41"/>
to perſist in vehemencie of perſecution againſt our religion: let vs finde you ſo far to harken vnto vs, that to retaine the name of lavve-makers, you vvill retaine ſome proportio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> &amp; a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nologie (as all ſo named must doe) vvith the moſt auntient lavve of God, of nature, nations, and this kingdome, not to puniſh tvvice one and the ſame offence. If by ſtrong hand you will haue that to be offence, which vve aſſure our ſelues is ſo far fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that name and nature, that the contrary is great and heigh offence to God; <hi>Non conſurgat, duplex tribulatio,</hi> and <hi>afflixi te, non iterum affligam:</hi> and againe. <hi>Deus non punit bis in idipſu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</hi> And as a dou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble puniſhments is not to be inflicted for one of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence, ſo by theſe lavves, <hi>pro menſura delicti erit &amp; plagarum modus;</hi> vvhich our aunti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent lavves in our great charter of England follovve: <hi>Nullus liber homo amercietur, ſed ſecundum modum delicti ipſius, ſaluo tene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mento ſuo (Magna Charta cap. 14.)</hi> Peruſe if it pleaſe you, but the heades of the punish<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments prouided against vs, for ſundry reſpects, (queſtionable vvhether any offence or no) and ſhal perceaue that your lavvs do not impoſe you or proſecute ſuch ſeuere penalties by many de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grees vpon ſins, that certainly and by al iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:14775:41"/>
are confeſſed and acknovledged to be ſinnes, yea, and great ſinnes againſt the lawe of God, nature, all nations, &amp; this Kingdome.</p>
                           <p>By this we hope you vnderstand, that if you wil haue example, either in heauen, or earth to follow, your perſecutions must die, or must diminiſh, for we haue yeelded ful ſatisfactio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to all your pretended reaſons to perſecute vs. That which remaineth, wee deſire you to conſider what a reſemblance there is, or ſhould be be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene yours &amp; the heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ly court, fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> whence the irreuocable law is proceeded, &amp; with great terror published: <hi>Woe to the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that make vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iuſt lawes, and writing, haue written iniu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice, that in iudgeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t they might oppreſſe the poore, and do violence to the cauſe of the humble of my people, that widdowes might be their prey, and the ſpoyle of fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therles.</hi> So beſeeching the almightie, that in theſe and other cauſes, in that heigh Court now in hand, you may in ſuch ſort proceed, as may be to his honor and glory, the ſecuritie &amp; good of his maiestie, his of-ſpring &amp; posterity, and this common wealth, we leaue you to Gods holy protection.</p>
                           <closer>
                              <signed>Your wel-wiſhing Countrymen, kinſmen, alliance, &amp; frie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ds, the Catholike Recuſa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts of this realme of Engla<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d.</signed>
                           </closer>
                        </div>
                     </body>
                  </floatingText>
               </q>
               <p>
                  <pb n="82" facs="tcp:14775:42"/>An other alſo of the like tenure, which here enſueth, was then with the ſame aſſent ſubſcribed with 23. handes of the chiefeſt Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholike gentlemen of England, and preſented to the chiefe Secretarie of eſtate, potent in thoſe times in court and councell, and as the Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>likes then feared, not equally effected towards them, though neuer ſo innocent and wel-de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeruing, who was one of them who with other of the councell declared to diuers of theſe gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tlemen (as they confidently reported vpon their reputation) that the Kings pleaſure was they ſhould paye no more the penaltie of twentie pounds a month for their recuſancie; and after when hee had perſwaded his maieſtie to the contrarie, denyed his former aſſertion, of the releace thereof, although the gentlemen moſt ſincere and iuſte, ſtill inſiſted and maintayned that this meſſadge was ſo deliuered vnto them: which alſo the then Earle of Northampton, L. Henry Howard, did freely confeſſe &amp; acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge to be moſt true. And the ſame Catholiks were more then iealous, that this practiſe of co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſpiracie was no great ſecret to that Secretary, long before diuers of them that were actors in it, and by him named Catholikes, were acquain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted with it. We may not enter into iudgement, where men are not defamed of ſuch inuenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, to entrappe thoſe they doe not affect: for the reſt, let M. Howes his hiſtorie of that mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter make relation who it was, a great proteſtant
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:14775:42"/>
that had more, or not much inferiour knowe ledge of it by his relation, then ſome that wer-put to death for concealing it. But howſoeuer, the petition followeth in theſe tearmes.</p>
               <q>
                  <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                     <body>
                        <div type="petition">
                           <head>
                              <hi>TO THE RIGHT HO<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>NORABLE, ROBERT,</hi> Earle of Saliſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>burie, chiefe Secretarie of eſtate to his Maieſtie: the petition of the Catholicks of England.</head>
                           <p>IF the corrupted and obſcured vnderstan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding of men not knowing God, could among other cloudes and mystes of ignorance, be ſo far blinde in that wherein the lawe &amp; light of nature it ſelfe doth giue ſufficient instru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to all people and nations, that Princes and rulers in authoritie are to be honoured and obeyed: yet the heauenly and ſupernatural il<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lumination doth clearly deliuer all Christians (eſpecially Catholikes) from ſuch darkeneſſe and want of dutie, giuing knowledge that <hi>e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerie ſoule muſt be ſubiect to ſuperiour po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wers;</hi> that God is he, <hi>per quem reges reg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant:</hi> and, <hi>he that reſiſteth power, reſiſteth the ordinance of God.</hi>
                           </p>
                           <p>
                              <pb n="84" facs="tcp:14775:43"/>Wherefore vvee your Lordshippes humble ſuppliants, the Lay Catholiques of this King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, ſo long probationers for religious cauſes, haue euer in our hearts, wordes and workes abandoned all contrarie proceedings, as a Babi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lonian building and inſurrection againſt the might and commande of heauen: damnable and rebellious vnto all regall and princely power, peace, and vnitie on earth. Therefore being ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moniſhed by the vviſest King, that there is as well, <hi>tempus loquendi,</hi> as <hi>tacendi:</hi> and occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions of theſe times being ſuch as inforce vs to ſpeake, leaſt by ſilence vvee might be cenſured by ſome no equall minded-men vnto vs, to be ſuſpected criminal in that, vvherein as al mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of that nature vve doe, and euer did, by long-knovvne experience, stande most inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent: vvee therefore protest, concerning the late conſpiracie, that vvee doe condemne it for a moſt impious, vnnatural, barbarous, and execrable offence, againſt the lavve of nature, the ſacred vvord of God, and the canons and practiſe of the holy Catholike Church, wherein vvee doe liue: to vvhich, no pretence of ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſse, no petence of Religion, no pretence of priuate or publicke authoritie, can giue vvar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant to make it lavvful. And vvee take God
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:14775:43"/>
to vvitneſſe that vvee vvere neither con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenting, co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſpiring or priuie to that, or any ſuch w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                                 <desc>•</desc>
                              </gap>ked deſignement, but the very reme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>brance that any ſuch enterpriſe should be intended or deuiſed by any ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> (eſpecially bearing the name of a Catholik.) is the continuall ſorrow of our hearts, and among al tribulations, the obiect of our greateſt griefe.</p>
                           <p>And for this preſent, and all future times we offer, profeſse, and promiſe, as great, ample, true, and faithful obedience, loyaltie, &amp; dutie to his Maiestie, as though he were a Prince of our owne religion: as much as any our aun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cestours in this Kingdome did yeelde to any his heighnes progenitors, Kings and Princes thereof, or as is required of Catholike ſubiects in other countries to their Protestant rulers, or as any Protestant ſubiects obſerue or per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forme to their Proteſtant or Catholike Soue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raignes, in ciuill obedience: That neither vvee can offer, nor his Maiestie or estate require more of vs, all worlds and generations of me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, Catholikes, Proteſtants, Christians, Pagans, &amp; whatſoeuer in this and all other Kingdomes, past, preſent, and to come, wil witneſſe for vs. And for our ſinceritie, dutifull and obedient meaning herein, wee appeale to all our perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cutors,
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:14775:44"/>
their most strict, politicke, and cunning inquiries and examinations of our behauiour, and carriage from time to time, by which vvee ſtand as clearely vnſpotted, as irreprehenſible, as irreprooueable, as dutiful in all ciuil reſpects and duties, as any Proteſtant in this Nation.</p>
                           <p>Therefore, Right honorable, if ſome fewe vnhappie men of our religion haue made tra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſsion of their alleageance, we hope it shalbe no motiue to change your graue and vnreſol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued minde from thinking it vndue to impoſe a burthen vpon innocents, for the fact of the guiltie, according to your owne excelle<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t ſpeeche heeretofore vſed, and now at this preſent: <hi>So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lum necis artifices arte perire ſua.</hi> And your Lordſhips most chriſtian deſire, of one vnifor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitie in true religion in this kingdome, bring<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth no ſmale hope vnto vs, that now at last, our ſo-long and many times in humble maner requeſted petitions concerning our not com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming to your churches, may by your honoura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble mediation to his Maieſtie, be brought to tryall, by the learned of both parties, whether without committing ſinne, it may be done by vs, which wee take to be the onely meanes to bring this kingdome to your ſo-much deſired vniformitie in religion.</p>
                           <p>
                              <pb n="87" facs="tcp:14775:44"/>For if your Proteſtant novv aſſembled, or best learned doctors, can and doe prooue it law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full to our learned diuines, vve abſolutely offer to performe it, vvithout delay or further ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ception. And may it pleaſe your Lordſhip to call to minde, the ordinarie knowne practiſe of Catholikes and Protestants in France, Helue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, Germanie and other countries, where they communicate in ciuill ſocieties, and not in chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches, and ſpirituall communications: vvhich pleadeth that our refuſull is not ſingular, but hauing ground and patronage, both from Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholiques and Protestants in this point. Our confidence now is, that his Maieſtie, your ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour, and the ſtate, will not take this our humble and neceſſarie petition in euill parte, conſidering that catholique Emperours, Kings of France and other Princes, haue granted the like to their Protestant ſubiects, and this in thoſe countries vvhere no other Religion, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the Catholique Romane Religion hath bene publicklie exerciſed at any time, ſince their firſt conuerſion from Paganiſme.</p>
                        </div>
                     </body>
                  </floatingText>
               </q>
               <p>
                  <pb n="88" facs="tcp:14775:45"/>All theſe petitions being preſented accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to their titles at that time, though the two firſt to his Maieſtie were printed, and the booke after his maner anſwered by D. Norton a Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtant Biſhoppe, yet he neuer tooke notiſe of either of thoſe petitions, or any one ſentence of them: and the Parlament was as ſilent, for that preſented vnto it. Onely this Secretaty was ſo much diſtaſted with the gentlemen that ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigned it, that hee tolde M. Anthony Skinner, who preſented it vnto him, that if they were preſent, he would ſet them all by the heeles, a puniſhment for rogues, &amp; not for men of their worth and reputation. There was no other an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwere made to theſe petitions, but onely this, the oath was enacted, and after proſecuted with ſuch violence as the world can witneſſe, ſuch accompt and regarde hath bene made of our miſerie by theſe Proteſtants.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Whether any reformatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> may be found in the preten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded reformers of religion for Catholikes to fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low. And firſt of King Henry the <hi>8.</hi> with whome neither Catholikes nor Proteſtants now ioyne in Religion.</head>
               <p>NOW, ſeeing if we be in errour, we can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not poſſible by all meanes we can work, procure that the learned proteſtant biſhops, and doctors, who haue controlled all the chriſtian world in their ſecret aſſemblies, will vndertake
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:14775:45"/>
to inſtruct a few Prieſts of England, but ſuffer in their proceedings many thouſandes of Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholikes by this meanes to be tyrannized ouer both in bodies and ſoules: let vs returne to the firſt founders of this religion in England. The father King Henry the 8. his yong ſonne and daughter, and ſee if wee can finde any motiue in their proceedings to mooue vs from our er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ror, if we be in error. And firſt to begin with the firſt, the father in this new Religion, and ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall power, all Proteſtant antiquaries, <hi>Foxe, Parker, Stowe, Holinshed, Cambden, Howes,</hi> and the reſt entreating of this matter aſſure vs, both that King Henrie the 8. and his fit inſtrument <hi>Cranmer,</hi> for a cleargie man, were the principall and firſt actors in this Tragedie (<hi>Foxe tom. 2. in Henr.</hi> 8, <hi>and Cranmar. Parker antiq. Brit. in Cranm. Stow hist. in Henr. 8. Holinsh. ibi. Theater of great Brit<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>in eod. Howes historial praef. Cambd. praef. hiſt. Eliz. &amp;c.</hi>) and the occaſion King Henry tooke to make his reuolt from the Church of Rome, becauſe the pope would not conſent for his putting away his wife Queene Katherine, that holie Ladie of Spayne. For before that time, king Henry was ſo obedient a childe to the Sea, and Religion of Rome, that by the pen of the bleſſed Biſhop Fiſher (whom hee after put to death, for denyal of his aſſumpted Supreamacy) in his owne name he defended them againſt the ſcurrilous bookes of Martin Luther: and was for that ſtiled by the Pope, <hi>Defenſor fidei, defendor of
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:14775:46"/>
the faith (Henr. 8. l. cont. Luther)</hi> which his Maie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtie King Iames ſtill vſeth by vertue of that do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation.</p>
               <p>One of late among the reſt, with greateſt warrant, ſpeaking of this his firſt reuoult, hath theſe wordes <hi>(Hovves historicall praeface to his Hist. in Henry 8.) This was done after the king was deuorced from</hi> Catherine <hi>of Spaine, his firſt wife, with whom he had liued aboue twenty yeares, and by her had fiue children. The cleargie nor parlame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t notwithstanding the Kings importunitie would ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer yeelde to the diuorce, by reaſon they could not finde any iust cauſe. The King made Cranmar Arch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bishop of Canterbury, who was very apt, and ready to performe the Kings will, and he denounced the ſentence of diuorce. Then the King, contrary to the good liking of all men, marryed</hi> Anne Bulleyne, <hi>by whom he had the Ladie Elizabeth. And then by acte of Parlament, made it treaſon against all men, that should ſay the marriage was not lawful. And pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently after her birth, he pickt a quarrell againſt Queene</hi> Anne, <hi>and then repealed the former acte, &amp; made a new acte of Parlament, whereby it was en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>acted, that it should be heigh treaſon, for any to iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtifie his former marriage to be lawfull, and the next day after her behedding, he marryed her hand-maid,</hi> Iane Seymor, <hi>and then declared the Ladie</hi> Eliza<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beth <hi>to be illegitimate.</hi> Thus word by word this Proteſtant hiſtorian: Then by this, &amp; ſuch like proceedings, as firſt bringing the cleargie into danger of Premunire, threats, importunities, and
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:14775:46"/>
ſuch practiſes, as theſe Proteſtants tel vs <hi>(Parker, Stow, Hollinshed, Theater, vt ſupr.)</hi> procuring the title of Supremacie to himſelfe in matters ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſiaſticall.</p>
               <p>This Proteſtant antiquarie thus proceedeth in this Kings proceedings: <hi>The king obtained the Eccleſiasticall ſupremacie into his particular poſſeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, and therewithal had power giuen him by parla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, to ſuruey &amp; reforme the abuſes of al Religious houſes &amp; parſons. But the King becauſe he would go the next way to worke, ouerthrew them, and razed them. Whereat many the Peeres and common people murmured, becauſe they expected, that the abuſes should haue bene onely reformed, and the reſt haue still remained. The general plauſible proiect, which cauſed the Parlaments conſent vnto the reformation, or alteration of the Monaſteries, was that the Kings exchequer should for euer be enriched, the Kingdome and nobilitie strengthened and encreaſed, and the common ſubiectes acquitted and freed from all for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer ſeruices and taxes: to witte, that the Abbots, Monkes, Friers, and Nunnes being ſuppreſſed, that then in their places should be created fourty Earles. threeſcore Barons, and three thouſand Knights, and fourtie thouſand ſouldiers, with skilfull captaines, and competent maintenance for them for euer, out of the antient church-reuenewes, ſo as in ſo doing, the King and his ſucceſſors should neuer want of trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure of their owne, nor haue cauſe to be beholding to the common ſubiect, neither should the people be any more charged with loanes, ſubſidies and fifteenes,
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:14775:47"/>
ſince which time there haue bene more statute laws, ſubſidies, and fifteenes, then in fiue hundred yeares before, and not long after that, the King had ſubſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies granted, and borrowed great ſommes of money, and dyed in debt, and the forenamed religious houſes were vtterly ruinate, whereat the cleargy, peeres, and co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon people, were all ſore grieued, but could not helpe it. He alſo ſupprest the knights of the Rhodes, and many faire hoſpitals. This was done after the king was diuorced from</hi> Catherine <hi>of Spaine his first wife. He began his raigne prodigally, reigned rigorouſly, liued proudly, and dyed diſtemperatly. Through feare and terrour he obtained an acte of Parlament, to diſpoſe of the right of ſucceſsio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in the Crowne, and then by his last will and testament con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to the law of God and nature, conueyes it from the lawful heyres of his eldest Sister, marryed to the king of Scotland, vnto the heires of</hi> Charles Bran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don <hi>and others, thereby to haue defeated preuented, and ſuppreſſed the vnqueſtionable, and immediate right from God, of our gratious Soueraigne king</hi> Iames. <hi>At his death he was much perplexed, and ſpake many things to great purpoſe, but being in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conſtant in his life, none durst trust him at his death.</hi> Thus your Proteſtant hiſtorian hath deſcribed this firſt proteſtant ſupreame head of the church in England.</p>
               <p>They that deſire more knowledge of him, may reſort to his owne ſtatutes, the Proteſtant Theater of Britanie, Sir Walter Raleigh his pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>face to his hiſtorie of the world: and a booke
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:14775:47"/>
of the tyrants of the world, publiſhed by the Proteſtants of Baſile, where they may find him a ſupreame head among them (<hi>ſtatut. Henr.</hi> 8. <hi>ab an. Regni 21. Theater of Brit. in Henr.</hi> 8. <hi>Walter Ral. hiſtor. of the world. praef. lib. of Tyran. Baſil.</hi>) And his ghoſtly father <hi>Cranmer</hi> his chiefe inſtrume<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t in thoſe moſte execrable ſinnes, for a Cleargie man was not inferiour vnto him. Hee was as your firſt proteſtantly ordained Archbiſhoppe Parker in his life, with others witneſſeth, both the mooued and moouing inſtrument of this king, in this, and many other his wicked deſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nements. Hee was of all the Religions of King Henry the 8. &amp; Edward the 6. He diuers times ſwore to the Pope, and was forſworne: Hee ſwore to King Henry the 8. and was forſworne, when he ſwore otherwiſe to king Edward his ſonne, and was publickly prooued a periured man: he was a chiefe executor of king Henrie the 8. his will, and within 24. houres of his death, a chiefe breaker thereof. He was a conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nued felon vnto him in his life, married againſt his lawes, making it felony in ſuch men: hee was for chaſtitie, to my reading the firſt, laſt, and onely trigamus, a Biſhoppe, husband of three wiues in the world. He counterfeited the hands and ſeales of 50. conuocation men, and among the reſt of the bleſſed martyr, Biſhop Fiſher. He gaue chiefe conſent, and ſwore, that Edwarde the 6. a childe of nine yeares old, was ſupreame head of the Church, had al iuriſdiction ſpiritual
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:14775:48"/>
in himſelfe <hi>(Parker antiq. Britan. in Cranmer. Foxe tom.</hi> 2. <hi>in Cranmer. Stow hiſtor. in Har.</hi> 8. <hi>Holinsh. Hiſt. of Engl. ibid. Theater of great Britanie in K. Henr. Godwyne Catalogue of Bishops in Canterbu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie in Tho. Cranmer. Stow, Holinsh, Theater, Foxe, and others in Q. Marie. and Edw. the</hi> 6. <hi>Harpesfield, in the life of B. Fisher)</hi> and all that Cranmar had he receaued from him, yea your Proteſtants wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, by the Proteſtant Confeſſions themſelues of <hi>Heluetia, Bohemia, Belgia, Augusta, Wittenberge, and Swe, that boyes could not take or giue ſuch power. (Th. Rogers pag.</hi> 140. <hi>artic.</hi> 23. <hi>Confeſſ. Hel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uet. Bohem. Belg. August. Wittenb. &amp;c.</hi>)</p>
               <p>If any thing now controuerſied, defended &amp; ſworne vnto, can make a man an heretike, Cra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mar profeſſing and ſwearing vnto them all, was an hereticke and traytor to God: If conſpiracie, open hoſtilitie, and rebellion to his true and lawfull prince, Queene Marie, doth make a man a traytor to his Soueraigne: If to be hiſſed in the publicke ſchooles of Oxford, in publike diſpu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation, after all theſe changes doth conuince a man, vndertaking ſo many matters, to be a man vnworthie and ignorant: If to recant hereſie, &amp; fall to it againe, putteth a man in caſe of relapſe of hereſie, all theſe thinges be written of this Archbiſhop, Archactor, Architector, Arch-here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticke, Arch-traytor, Arch-periured &amp; prophane wretch of your Religion, by your owne writers here cited, and were publickly to the eternal in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>famie of that vnhappie and graceleſſe man, and
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:14775:48"/>
his followers therein, prooued againſt him. Therefore, although King Henry the eight did rather differ from the Church of Rome in mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of Iuriſdiction ſpiritual (by his claymed Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>premacie) as your proteſtants teſtifie, and his lawes are witneſſes (<hi>Stow histor. in. Henr.</hi> 8. <hi>Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>linsh. and Theator ibid. ſtatut of K. Henrie</hi> 8. <hi>&amp;c.</hi>) the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> any way in matter of doctrine, Catholiks can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not in conſcience by your Proteſtants, ioyne either with him, or you therein, beeing the firſt (as they haue aſſured vs) that euer claymed it in this kingdome; and procuring it in ſo vile &amp; vnlawful maner, as your hiſtorians haue decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red; and practizing it to his wanton and ambiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous ende, againſt his owne conſcience. For al the foundatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s of our Religious houſes being <hi>pro re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>medio animaru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, to ſay Maſſe &amp; pray for their poſteri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie for euer. For the honor of God, the most bleſsed Vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin, and other Saints,</hi> as all our antiquities giue warrant to write: he in all his life time co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tinued in theſe doctrines, and at his death in his laſt will and teſtament, proteſted himſelfe to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue in that opinion (<hi>Bed. Henric. Hunt. Guliel. Malmesb. Roger. Houeden. Matth. West. Flor. Wigor. Camb. Stow. Holinsq. Theator, &amp;c.</hi>) And for the ſupremacie it ſelfe (as hath bene prooued in the time of Queene Elizabeth, and your proteſtant hiſtorian, hath ſufficiently inſinuated) he recan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted it (<hi>Booke intituled, Lesters common wealth</hi>) your Proteſtants wordes of him theſe be: <hi>At his death he was much perplexed, &amp; ſpake many things
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:14775:49"/>
to great purpoſe, but being vnconstant in his life, none durſt trust him at his death (Howes ſuper. hist. preface in Henry 8.</hi>) which relation from a prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant writer, can carrie no other conſtruction. And I take God to witneſſe, I haue heard my father (then liuing in Courte) often make rela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, that this king Henry the 8. at his death, was ſorie for his taking that title of ſupremacie vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon him, was willing to relinquiſh it, and la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boured to be reconciled to the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> promiſing if he liued, ſo far as he could to make reſtitution. But being demanded of him pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently to take order therein, he was preuented by death, and dyed with ſuch burthen and hor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ror of co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſcience, as chanceth in ſuch caſes: which this Proteſtant before aymeth at, when he ſaith, <hi>he was much perplexed, and ſpake many thinges to great purpoſe.</hi> Therefore the Catholikes of En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gland, are rather confirmed by this king, then weakned by him, in profeſſion of their holie faith.</p>
               <p>And though in his life he perſecuted and put to death many renowned Catholikes, for deniall of his ſupremacie, and ſacramentary Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtants (ſuch as thoſe in England now are) for heretikes, yet he neuer recalled this ſecond, as he did the firſt, neither made any new lawe, by which they were put to death, but left their triall to the auntient Canons of the Catholike Church; yet put thoſe Catholikes to death only by pretence of his new inacted Edict of his ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>premacie,
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:14775:49"/>
neuer heard of in England before, as Proteſtant antiquaries haue tolde vs. Therefore this firſt ſupreame head of religion in England, in all things confirmeth the religion of Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>likes, and condemneth that of Proteſtants: and this the more if we adde from your Proteſtant hiſtorians, how fraudulently, or rather forcebly he obtained his firſt colourable tytle to that his ſpirituall ſupremacie, by which he kept ſuch turbule<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t ſturres in this kingdome. A Proteſtant hiſtorian and an Eſquire by ſtate, as he ſtileth himſelfe, thus relateth it. <hi>William Martine Eſq. in hiſtor. of Henr.</hi> 8. <hi>pag.</hi> 388.389.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Cardinal</hi> Wolſey <hi>being dead, the King by his Councel was informed, that all the cleargie of En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gland was guiltie of premunire: becauſe in al things they ſupported and maintained the authoritie, and power legatine of the Cardinal: wherefore to preuent miſchiefe, before it fell vpon them, they gaue to the King for their redemption, and for their pardon, the ſomme of one hundreth thouſand pounds, and by a publicke instrument in writing, ſubſcribed, and ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led by the Bishops and fathers of the Church; they acknowledged the King within his owne kingdomes and dominions, to be ſupreame head of the Church.</hi> Thus vniuſtly he procured that vnlawful prero<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gatiue, &amp; more vniuſtly as before, made his wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked vſe therof. I neede proceede no further in his proceedings, for they ar dead with him: the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent proteſtant ſtate, as his owne childre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> before, by lawes and Parlaments condemne them; all
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:14775:50"/>
Proteſtants in the worlde reiect them, and hee himſelfe before his death (by the moſt manerly faſhion he could) refuſed his title of ſuprema<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie, in which he moſt differed from the church of Rome, as I haue brought Proteſtant witneſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes before: therefore Catholiks are rather con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmed, then weakned in their religion, by the proceedings of this King.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>That English catholikes cannot be perſwaded vnto, but much diſſwaded from Proteſtant Religion, by the Protestant proceedings in the time of King Edward the 6.</head>
               <p>NOW let vs come to the next temporall rule, that claymed ſupremacie in ſpiritual matters in England: King Edward the 6. he was but 9. yeares olde, when this charge was layed vpon him, yet he was elleuen yeares olde, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> your religion was firſt borne in this nation, in the ſecond or third yeare of his raigne, as all lawes and hiſtories of that time giue recorde. (<hi>Parl.</hi> 2. <hi>&amp;</hi> 3. <hi>Edw.</hi> 6. <hi>Stow hiſt. in Edw.</hi> 6. <hi>Holinsh. Theater, and others ibid.</hi>) So this childe begot it, and his ſiſter Q Elizabeth nurſed it. We knowe for ſhame you will not tye vs, to the cenſure of an infant king; then you muſt appeale to thoſe that inſtructed, and directed him in ſo great a buſineſſe, Theſe were temporall, and ſpirituall, and chiefly thoſe that were of councell, and had ſworne otherwiſe to King Henry the 8.
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:14775:50"/>
during his life, liued in his Religion, and after his death continued the ſame vnder this yong king in his beginning and firſt Parlament (<hi>Parl. 1. of Edw. 6. Stow. Holinsh. &amp; in k. Edw. 6.</hi>) were executors of the laſt will and teſtament of king Henry the eight, in which concerning matters of truſt in religion, they truely executed no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing at all: but in the exheredation of his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ieſties holy Mother and himſelfe, as much as they could they executed it (<hi>Howes historial pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>face ſupr. Stow, Holinsh. Theater, &amp; in Q. Marie &amp; Edward. 6.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The chiefeſt of theſe for ſpiritual men was Cranmer their Archbiſhop, and the reſt of the Biſhops of that time that were not Catholikes, of which we finde but two, onely <hi>Hooper</hi> and <hi>Ferrar</hi> put to death for their Religio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> by Queene <hi>Marie</hi>: For <hi>Cranmer, Ridlie,</hi> and <hi>Latimer</hi> were condemned for treaſon (<hi>Foxe tome.</hi> 2. <hi>Monumen. in Q. Marie. Godwyne Catalogue of Bishops of K. Ed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards time.</hi>) and what can we accompt of the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion of theſe two, changing their profeſſion ſo often with king Henry and K. Edward? and <hi>Ferrar</hi> (to vſe your Biſhops wordes) <hi>was thrust out of the Bishoppricke, in the beginning of Queene</hi> Marie, <hi>for being married, and ended his life in the fyer</hi>: more for being deſperate how to liue, then for loue of Religion, ſo far as we can gather. (<hi>Godwyn in S. Daudis 79. Robert Ferrar</hi>) The o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, <hi>Hooper (Godwyn in Worceſter.</hi> 75. <hi>Glocester.</hi> 2. <hi>Iohn Hooper</hi>) a man of ſuch conſcience, as your
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:14775:51"/>
Biſhop writeth, that being made Biſhop by the childe king <hi>anno</hi> 1550. <hi>Bishop of Gloceſter held alſo the Biſhopricke of Worceſter in commendam by li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cence of King Edward the ſixt</hi>; this is his com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendation. The reſt that fled not the Realme for treaſon (which were not of your Proteſtant religion, but Puritanes in forraine countries) were depriued in England for being married, which by no Religion Biſhops might doe: ſuch were <hi>Bush</hi> of Briſtow, <hi>Harley</hi> of Hereford, <hi>Hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gate</hi> of Yorke and others that became Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>likes <hi>(Godwyn in Brist. Heref. Yorke, &amp;c.) Couer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dale</hi> was ſet at libertie by Q. <hi>Marie,</hi> and of ſo ſmall eſteeme with you in the beginning of Q. Elizabeth her raigne, that no Biſhopricke was allowed him.</p>
               <p>Now let vs come to your chiefe temporall councellours then, theſe were by their owne creation, the Dukes of Sommerſet and Nor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thumberland, called Protectors to the young king <hi>(Stow and Holinsh. and Theater. K. Edw. 6. and Q. Marie)</hi> the firſt baſely put to death in that time for felonie: the other for treaſon and open rebellion againſt Q. <hi>Marie</hi>: And after hee had bene thus with Cranmar, the chiefe inſtrument to ouerthrowe Catholike Religion, and ſet vp Proteſtancie in the time of that yong king: hee plainely recanted his new faith, and was recon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciled to the Church of Rome. And yet among theſe vnworthie men, vnder that yong king there were but 6. Biſhops, and 6. others that
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:14775:51"/>
made the Church-bookes of their religion the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: <hi>(Statut. An.</hi> 3. <hi>Edw. 6. cap.</hi> 12. <hi>Foxe, Stowe, and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers in Edw. 6.)</hi> and for religion it ſelfe, they had no Canons, articles, or decrees of it in all the time of that king. <hi>Howes</hi> your hiſtorian thus writeth of it: Edward, <hi>at nine yeares of age ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeded his father, and then the Church vvas fleeſt a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine, the Bishoprickes cut and pared, all Chantries ſupprest, the Bishoppricke of Durrham allienated. By all vvhich, the Kings Exhequer vvas very litle enriched, neither vvas the common vvealth eaſed, or benefited; nor the auntient nobilitie any vvay digni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied, onely ſome fevv preferred. The Earldome of Northumberland giuen to the</hi> Suttons, <hi>vvho obtay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned the title of the Duke of Northumberland. In the first and ſecond yeare of his raigne, the Maſse vvas vvholly ſupprest, and part of King Dauids Pſalmes vvere turned into english verſe, by</hi> Hopkins <hi>and</hi> Sterneholde, <hi>Groomes of the Kings chamber, and ſet them to ſeuerall tunes, conſiſting of galliards and meaſures. The Duke of Sommerſet, vncle to the King by the mothers ſide, being the Kings Protector, did all things in the Kings name, and inclyned ouer-much to the ſubtile counſel of his ſecret enemie, the Duke of Northumberland, vvho vvas fully bent to defeat and ſuppreſſe the apparant heires of God and nature vnto the Crovvne, and to preferre the heires of the Duke of Suffolke, according to the iniurious determination of k. Henrie the eight. For the better effecting vvhere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, they made a combination, vvhich had as good ſuc-ſucceſse, as ſo bad a practiſe deſerued. The Protector
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:14775:52"/>
among other things that croſſed his greatneſſe in po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pularitie was, the ſpoyling of churches and chappels, the defacing of auncient tombes and monuments, &amp; namely, twelue goodly tombes in Christ-church: his attempting was to pull downe all the Belles in parish Churches, and to leaue but one Bell in a steeple, whereat the commonalitie were reddie to rebell Hee raigned ſeuen yeares, mette with a tricke of trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon.</hi> He meaneth that he was poyſoned by his proteſtant Protector Cranmar, &amp; other pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtants of that moſt wicked combination.</p>
               <p>They that deſire to know more of that yong kings times, may reſort to your Proteſtant hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtories of Foxe, Stowe, Holinſhed, Speede (<hi>Foxe tom. 2. in king Edw. Holinsh. and Theater ibid. In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iunctions an. 1. Ed.</hi> 6.) and the childiſh Iniuncti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons in matters of Religion, ſet out in the name of that Nouice, and Nouecins ſupreame head of your church: where he may finde the chiefe care of the councell and executors, left by king Henry the eight, ſpiritual and temporal, to loade themſelues with new and great titles, and ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nours of dignitie, grow riche, by the laſt ruines of the Church, and to be of no ſetled religion at all: For we doe not finde either in hiſtories, or in confeſſion of Proteſtants diligently collected by them, or in any priuate or publike monu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, any forme, faſhion, ſhape, articles, canons or decrees of Religion, either vnder king Henry the 8. k. Edward the 6. or Q. Elizabeth, vntill
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:14775:52"/>
her fourth yeare, anno 1562. when the booke of the artickles of your religion was firſt contry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued and publiſhed to the world. <hi>Booke of Articles of Religion, an. 1562.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Therefore wee may not ioyne with theſe men in Religion, as neither you doe, eſpeciallie with king Henrie the eight, but rather mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uaile why you and all that clayme title to reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion from them, do not finde great motiues ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to bethinke what wrongs they did vnto vs, then perſiſt in heaping new and more preſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures, and perſecutions vpon the Catholikes of your owne nation, and kindred. For you haue heard from your Proteſtants before, that they obtayned that their power againſt the Relige<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous houſes of England, onely vpon this motiue to reforme abuſes, if they could finde them: <hi>To create and maintaine for the perpetual defence and ſecuritie of this Kingdome. 40. Earles, 60. Barons,</hi> 300. <hi>knights, and foureſcore thouſand ſouldiers, with skilful captaines, and competent maintenance for them all for euer, out of the auntient Church re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenewes</hi>: and yet to leaue for the maintenance of religious parſons, profeſſing and liuing in the perfect way of chriſtian Religion, chaſtitie, obedience, and pouertie, watchings, faſtings, prayers, and auſteritie of life, continued &amp; maintained here from the comming of S. Io<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeph of Aramathia into this Iland by our kings, euen the Pagan kings, <hi>Aruiragus, Marius,</hi> and <hi>Caillus,</hi> and other Chriſtian Princes, and
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:14775:53"/>
holy founders after, to theſe dayes <hi>(antiq. Glaston. apud Lel. in aſſert. Arthur. Capgraue in S. Ioſeph. &amp; S. Patric. &amp; proteſt. hiſtor.)</hi> which neither the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion of King Henrie the 8. King Edward the 6. Queene Elizabeth, or King Iames, did or doth condemne.</p>
               <p>Neither can any of them (as theſe Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantes haue before bene witneſſes) diſſallow of their Maſſes and prayers for the dead, but ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledged the contrarie opinion to be here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticall and damnable: yet both to the temporall and ſpirituall dammage of many thouſands, fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that time they ſtill perſeuer in that eſtate of in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iuſtice, ſo obnoxious to reſtitution, and are ſo farre from performing King Henrie the eight his condition, to maintaine ſo many thouſand ſouldiers &amp; others, and eaſe their kingdome of taxes and contributions, that they are not now able to performe the firſt, nor to maintaine their dignities without the other. In all which, the Catholikes of England, are onely innocent, and yet they alone for their innocencie, are con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demned, and perſecuted.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>THAT THE PROCEEDINGS OF Q. Elizabeth ar noe warrant for proteſtants to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecute Catholicks, nor noe true conuiction, but rather a confirmation of the Romane Catholicke Religion: by the writings of English proteſtants themſelues.</head>
               <p>
                  <pb n="89" facs="tcp:14775:53"/>ALl theſe proteſtant arguments conclude much more ſtrongely againſt the procee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dings of Queene Elizabeth in theſe matters: for if it was publickly addiuged for lawe in the time of kinge Henry the ſeuenth (our lawes remayning the ſame) <hi>That the parlament could not make the king beeing a lay man, to haue ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall Iuriſdiction. (temporibus Henrici 7.</hi>) How much more an vnpoſſible thinge is it, to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>title a woman, and ſuch a woman to that dig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitie by ſuch donation? for firſt euen by our pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtants, it is the Pepuzian hereſie to ſay a wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man at all is capable of that ſpirituall vocatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſhee ſtooke vppon herſelfe, and preſumed to impart to others. (<hi>Epiphan. &amp; Aug. in haereſ. Pepuzian.</hi>) And thereupon your proteſtants aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure vs: <hi>The Queens maiesties parſon was neuer capable of any part of ſpiritual power: (Ormerod. proteſt. Aſſert. an. 1604. pag. 218.)</hi> Then much leſſe of that ſupreame power. And if ſhee had been a man, yett in that caſe your proteſtant hiſtorians before haue told vs, made illegiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mate by publicke parlament, the Kinge, Lords ſpirituall, and temporall with the reſt, there muſt haue beene as greate a power to recall yt, which was not in that her firſt parlament, for the Lords ſpirituall, whoe onely haue power in ſuch caſes, did vtterly diſſent to yeeld her any ſuch priuiledge, ſoe that noe man, or com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany that had power of diſpenſations, in ſuch things, diſpenſed with her, but contrary.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="90" facs="tcp:14775:54"/>Againe, it is a maxime in the Lawes (as you Lord Cooke writeth (<hi>l. 4. fol, 23.) nemo po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>test plus iuris in alium transferre qnàm ipſe habet. None can giue more power to an other, then they haue to giue,</hi> and the contrarie is vnpoſſible: Therefore ſeeing no Parlament that euer was in England, when all the Biſhops and Abbots, and chiefe ſpirituall men it euer had were aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſembled, had at any time, either for themſelues, or to giue vnto any other, that ſupreame ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall power, but as your Biſhops haue told vs before, it was wholly in the Pope of Rome euer from our conuerſion, and ſo could neuer be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riued to King Henry the eight, or Edward the ſix. (<hi>Parker antiquit. Britan. in Cranmer. Polydor. Virg. in Henr.</hi> 8. <hi>l. vlt. histor. &amp;c.</hi>) it is much more ſtronge againſt Q. Elizabeth, both for her ſexe, and the other incapabilitie, as Proteſtants aſſure vs. And for her or any to clayme it, by that Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lament wherein ſhee tooke it vpon her, is a thing more then to be wondred at: for all men of that Parlament, which had any ſpiritual iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſdiction (as the Catholike Biſhops) did by all meanes reſiſt and contradict it: and the words of the ſtatute (as your Proteſtants haue publi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed it) by which ſhee tooke vpon her to exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſe it, and perſecute Catholikes onely by pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence of this power there giuen vnto her, are theſe: <hi>Most humbly beſeech your moſt excellent Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iestie your faithful and obedient ſubiects, the Lordes Spiritual, and Temporal, and the vvhole commons in
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:14775:54"/>
this your preſent Parlament aſſembled.</hi> That the ſupreame power ſpirituall, ſhould be in that Queene, when it is euident by all our Proteſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t hiſtories, that not one Lord Spirituall, either deſired it, or conſented vnto it, but all repugned and gaine-ſaid it; and for that cauſe were com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted to priſon, or otherwiſe moſt grieuouſly afflicted. (<hi>Stow histor. an. 1. Elizab. Holinsh. Thea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter. an. 1. Eliz. Cambd. annal. rerum Anglic. in</hi> 1. <hi>Elizab. &amp;c.</hi>) And yet there was not any man in that Parlament, that could giue vnto her, if ſhe had bene capable (as ſhe was not) the leaſt ſpiritual iuriſdiction ouer the leaſt pariſh in England.</p>
               <p>And if ſhe had not inſiſted in her fathers ſtep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pes of flatterie, terrors, &amp; diſſimulatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, promiſes of great matters without performa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce, &amp; in ſome degrees (by the cunning of ſome about her without conſcience) exceeded him, ſhee might haue founde as little applauſe, and conſent in the Lords temporall and others; For vſing all meanes ſhe could, to further her ſtrange procee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dings, (partly to be hereafter from her Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant writers remembred) yet shee found ſuch and ſo manifeſt reaſons oppoſed againſt her, that the ſcarres of thoſe wounds then giuen to your religion, will neuer be recouered. A principall antiquarie among you writeth (<hi>Cambden Annal. in Eliz. pag.</hi> 26.) that the Lord Vicount Moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tague, which a little before had bene Ambaſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dour at Rome, with Biſhop <hi>Thursby</hi> of Ely, for
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:14775:55"/>
the reconciling of England to the Church of Rome in Queene Maries time, publickly in par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lament theſe oppoſed.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Hic ex Religionis ardore, &amp; honoris ratione acri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter instabat, magno Angliae dedecori eſſe, ſi ab Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stolica ſede, cui nuper ſe ſubmiſſe reconciliarat, mox deficeret. Hee out of loue of religion and care of ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour, did earneſtly vrge, how great a shame it would be to England, if it should ſo ſoone reuoult from the Sea Apostolike, to which it had lately ſubmiſsiuelie reconciled it ſelfe: and would turne to greater dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger if excommunicated, it by ſuch defection be expo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, to the rage of neighboring enemies. Hee in the name of the nobilitie, and all degrees in England, in their name had done obedience to the Pope of Rome, and muſt needes performe it. Therefore he vrgently beſought them, that they would not depart from the Romane Sea, to which they were indebted, both for first receauing the faith from thence, and from thence hauing it continually preſerued.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>This was ſufficiently prooued at that time of the reconciliation of England to the Church of Rome, in open Parlament alſo by Cardinall Pole, as your firſt proteſtantly ordeyned Arch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bish. in theſe wordes affirmeth (<hi>Parkerant. Brit. in Reginald. Polo) Ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>c in ſulae nobilitatem, atque glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riam Dei prouidentiae, atque beneficientiae ſoli accep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ta ferendam, ſed tamen viam ipſam atque rationem qua hac nobilitas atque gloria parta est, ſede Roma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>na nobis prima ſemperque monstratam, &amp; patefa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctam fuiſſe. In Romana exinde fidei vnitate nos ſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:14775:55"/>
perſeueraſſe, fuiſſeque nostram antiquiſsimam Romanae eccleſiae ſubiectionem. The noblenes of this Iland, for being the first of all the Prouinces of the worlde, that receaued the Christian faith, and the glorie thereof, is to be acknowledged to haue procee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded from the prouidence and goodneſſe of God, yet the way it ſelfe and meanes, by which this nobilitie &amp; glory was wonne vnto it, was first &amp; alwaies shew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed and layde open vnto vs from the Sea of Rome: wee haue alwaies from that time perſeuered in the vnity of the Romane faith, and our ſubiection to the Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane Church is moſt auntient.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And this reconciling of England then to the Romane Church, was ſo ioyful and honorable a thing to this natio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, that to vſe your Proteſtant Archbiſhops wordes (<hi>Parker antiquit. Britan. in Polo) In Synodo decretum eſt, vt dies ille quo ponti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fici Romano authoritas reſtituta fuerit, quotannis feſtus dies celebraretur, atque Anglicanae eccleſiae re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conciliatio diceretur. It was decreede in a Synode, that the daye on which authoritie was reſtored to the Pope of Rome, should yeerely be kept holie daie, and called, the Reconciliation of the Church of En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gland.</hi> Abbot Fecknham (<hi>in Parlm. Elizab.</hi>) in his oration to that Parlament of Q. Elizabeth hath thus: <hi>Damianus and Fugatianus as Ambaſſadours from the Sea Apostolike of Rome, did bring into this Realme</hi> 1400. <hi>yeares paſt, the very ſame religion, whereof wee are now in poſſeſsion, and that in the latine tongue, as the auntient hiſtoriographer Domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus Gylduas witneſſeth, in the prologue and begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:14775:56"/>
of his booke of the Britaine hiſtories,</hi> which he would not haue dared to vtter, in that time and place, but that then he could produce that anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quitie to be his warrant: which with many o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers condemning the new religion of Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtants, are by them ſuppreſſed. All the Biſhops (of whom more hereafter) and whom tearmeth your Proteſtant glorious &amp; renowned men, <hi>ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmate refragati ſunt. Did ſtoutly giue their voyces againſt this innouation.</hi> They offered publicke defence by diſputation of Catholike Religion, both for doctrine and iuriſdiction. <hi>Cambden An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal. pag. 26. in appart. ad annal. pag. 36 Maſon lib. 3. conſecrat. pag. 206. cap. 5. Stow hist. an. 1. Eliz. Holinsh. ibid. Godwyn. Catol.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But the Proteſtants knowing how their chie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſt champions, had bene before ſo conuinced by them, that they were hiſſed by the auditors, durſt not come to triall. But the Parlament be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning on the 23. day of Ianuary, they preſently proceeded to make Queene Elizabeth ſupreme head of the Church, and by that title to make a religion what pleaſed her, and her few fauori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes, which by ſuch indirect meanes, as is heere teſtified by theſe Proteſtants, they brought to paſſe in the beginning of that Parlament, and in the very firſt acte and ſtatute thereof. (<hi>Theater of great Brittaine. lib. 9. cap.</hi> 24. <hi>parag. 4. Godwyn Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tal. in the Bish. depriu. an.</hi> 1. <hi>Elizab. Parlament. 1. an. 1. Eliz. cap.</hi> And would neuer hearken to any diſputation whatſoeuer, vntill they had thus
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:14775:56"/>
obteyned their purpoſe, and vntill the laſt day of March two moneths after, as all Proteſtant hiſtories giue euidence.</p>
               <p>And when they had by onely 6. voyces of laye-men, condemned our learned Biſhops, and their holy religion: the religion of the vniuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſall Church of God, they would not then al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low them (though condemned thus vniuſtly) a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny diſputation at all, except they would accept of that bable and mockerie of diſputation, and all religion; which I haue from theſe Proteſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts remembred before (<hi>Cambden in Annal. lib. pag.</hi> 27.) Therefore let vs paſſe it ouer in this place, and deſire your inſtructing Proteſtants a little further to inſtruct and informe vs, how ſhee proceeded, and ſo ſtrangely preuailed in this matter. <hi>Orbe Christiano mirante, to the wonder of all the Christian world,</hi> for the prophane pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedings then vſed, as your Proteſtants before haue teſtified <hi>(Camben annal. ſupra.)</hi>
               </p>
               <p>So ſoone as ſhee was proclaimed Queene, &amp; long before her Coronation, <hi>by proclamation she ſilenced the Catholike Bishops and Cleargie not to preach, and by her Iniunctions, gaue warrant to her laye protestant commiſsioners, to giue licence to preach (Proclamation of Q. Elizabeth. an. 1. Stowe histor. an.</hi> 1. <hi>Elizab. Iniunctions of Q. Elizabeth, an.) Shee put in practiſe the oathe of Supremacie amongſt many which refuſed that oath, was the Lord Chancellour, D.</hi> Heath, <hi>Archbishop of Yorke, from whom shee tooke the priuie ſeale, and remitted it
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:14775:57"/>
to Sr. Nicholas Bacon (Stowe histor. in Queene Elizabeth an. reg.</hi> 1.) <hi>shee putt many from the cowncell, and tooke new cownſaylers: ſuis adiun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>xit,</hi> ſayth your beſt Antiquary, (<hi>Cambden Annal. in Elizabeth pag.</hi> 18.19) <hi>pro temporum ratione, Gulielmum Parrum, Marchionem Northamptoniae, Franciſcum Ruſſellum, comitem Bedfordiae, Thomam Parrum, Edwardum Rogers, Ambroſium Cauum, Franciſcum Knolles, &amp; Guilielmum Cecilium, pau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loque poſt Nicholaum Bacon, ſingulos protestantium doctrinam amplexos, nulloque ſub Maria loco: Quos vt reliquos, in eorum locum iam inde ſuffectos, ita temperauit &amp; cohibuit, vt ſibi eſſent deuotiſsimi, &amp; ipſa ſemper ſui iuris, nulli obnoxij.</hi> Shee ioyned to hyrs for the ſtate of the tyme, William Parr, Marqueſſe of Northampton, Francis Ruſſell, Earle of Bedford, Thomas Parr, Edward Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers, Ambroſe Caue, Francis Knolles, and William Cecile, and ſoone after Nicholas Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>con, all become proteſtants, in noe office vnder Q. Mary, which as the reſt which ſhee putt in for thoſe ſhee diſplaced, ſhee ſoe tempered, and kept them in awe, that they were moſte ſeruiceable to her, ſhee allwayes to doe what pleaſed her, none to contradict her.</p>
               <p>Shee concluded <hi>cum paruulis intimis (Camb<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den ſupr. pag. 22.23.) with a few most inward with her, de nobilibus à regio conſilio amouendis epiſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pis &amp; eccleſiasticis de gradu deijciendis, Iudicibus qui pro tribunalibus ſederunt, &amp; hirenanchis per ſingulos comitatus, qui regnante Maria re &amp; aeſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>matione
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:14775:57"/>
magni erant, hos locos deturbandos, &amp; le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gum ſeueritate coercendos, nulloſque niſi protestan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes ad rerum adminiſtrationem adhibendos, &amp; in collegia vtriuſque academiae coaptandos cenſuerunt, fimulque pontificios praeſides ex academijs, ſcholar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chas ex wintonienſi, Aetonienſi, caeteriſque ſcholis ſubmouendos.</hi> Q. Elizabeth preſently after the death of Q. Mary taketh order, with very few of her inward frends how to reſtore proteſtant Religion. The plott by them was, that new co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſions ſhould bee directed to iudges, with prouiſion, they ſhould not giue any office: new Iuſtices of peace, and ſheriffes ſhould bee made in all countries, the noble men ſhould bee put from the councell, Biſhops and eccleſiaſticall men diſplaced, all iudges and iuſtices of peace that were in eſtimation in the tyme of Q. Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, ſhould bee remoued in all ſhires, and ſeue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rely kept vnder, and none but proteſtants to bee admitted to gouernment in the comon wealth, and placed in the colledges of both vniuerſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, and all popiſh preſidents of howſes, and ſcholemaſters to bee renewed from Winceſter Eton and other ſcholes.</p>
               <p>And accordinge to this concluſion, this Eli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zabeth neyther beeing crowned Queene as yet, nor haueinge by any pretence power to meddle with the Title of Supreamacie, becauſe to ſpeake in your proteſtants words, (<hi>Stowe hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stor. an. 1. Eliz ab. statut. in parlam. an. 1. Mariae) Queene Mary restored all thinges according to the
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:14775:58"/>
church of Rome, reduced all eccleſiasticall iuriſdic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, vnto the papall obedience</hi>: yett to write in the ſame proteſtants pen and words: <hi>(Stowe hiſtor ſupr. an. 1. Eliz.) The Queene tooke an ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>act ſuruey of all her cleargie and officers of eſtate, and putt in practiſe the oath of ſupreamacie, and amongst many which refuſed that oathe, was the Lord chauncellor D. Heath Archbishop of yorke: shee committed the custody of the greate Seale vnto S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. Nicholas Bacon, a man moste malicious against pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſts, whoe from that tyme was called Lord keeper. Cambden ſupr. annal. pag. 27.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Haueing thus diſplaced through the king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome all catholicke magiſtrates, and diſſolued the catholicke parlament, continueinge at the death of her Syſter Queene Mary, and putt new proteſtant officers in their places, with all ſpeed ſhee ſommoned a parlament to begyn in Ianuary followeinge, within twoe moneths of her ſiſters death. (<hi>Stowe ſupr. Holinsh. hiſtor. an.</hi> 1. <hi>Elizab. Theater of Britan. 16. Cambd. Annal. ann. 1. Elizab.</hi>) And haueing thus prouided for a fitt company in the lower howſe of parlament, ſwearers to the ſupremacie, ſhee and her <hi>pauculi intimi,</hi> were as prouident to packe ſome in the vpper howſe alſoe. Therefore a fewe dayes be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the parlament, to ſpeake as your proteſtant, <hi>(Stowe an.</hi> 1. <hi>Elizab. Cambden annal. ſupr.) the</hi> 13. <hi>of Ianuary, the Queene in the Tower created Sr. William Parr, ob laeſam maiestatem ſub Maria gradu deiectum, attainted of treaſon in Q. Maryes
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:14775:58"/>
tyme, Lord marqueſſe of Northampton, Edward Sey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mor ſonne to the late Duke of Sommerſett, attain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, vicount Beuchamp, and Earle of Hertford: Tho. Howard ſecond ſonne of Tho. Duke of Norfolke, vicount Bindon; Sr. Oliuer Saint Ihon, Baron of Bletſoe; and Sr. Henry Carey, Lord Hounſdon. Qui ſinguli à pontificia Religione alieni, all which were alienated from the popes Religion,</hi> all which that Queene and her <hi>pauculi intimi, very fewe that con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſented vnto her,</hi> knew by that meanes would giue their voyces in parlament to what ſhee ſhould deſire, and not content with this, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeded ſoe in theſe indirect courſes, that as your proteſtants haue written: (<hi>Cambden Annall. pag. 27.) plures è proteſtantibus data opera, è comitatibus tum è ciuitatibus, &amp; burgis fuiſſe electos, &amp; Norfol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciae ducem, Arundeliaeque Comitem, inter proceres potentiſsimos, in ſuam ſiue rem, ſiue ſpem, Cecilium<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>que ſua ſolertia ſuffragia emendicaſſe. The papists complayned, that more protestants of ſett purpoſe were choſen out of Countries, cyties, and burroughts, and the Duke of Norfolke and Earle of Arundell moste potent amonge the nobilitie, eyther for their owne good, or hope (by the Queens promiſes of marriadge or ſuch things) and Cecyle by his cun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ninge had begged voyces.</hi> And to helpe and fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſoe bad a cauſe, the <hi>Queene herſelfe</hi> (your proteſtants words) <hi>openly protested at that tyme in parlament, that shee would neuer vexe, or trouble the Romane Catholicks, concerning any difference in Religion.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="100" facs="tcp:14775:59"/>Neyther did this Queene or hir <hi>pauculi in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>timi,</hi> Cecile and Bacon, take this ſtraunge courſe in hand, for diſlike of catholick Religion: for your Antiquary telleth vs of Q. Elizabeth her<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe: <hi>ad Romanae Religionis normam ſacra audi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ret, &amp; ſaepius confiteretur. Miſſam permiſit poſt mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tem Mariae &amp; litanias. Q. Elizabeth heard maſse af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the Romane order, often went to confeſsion, and after Q. Maryes death allowed maſſe and litanies, (Cambden in Apparatu pag. 13.)</hi> The like is as well knowne of thoſe her <hi>intimi</hi> at that tyme. But they had other little laudable ends, by proteſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tant proceedings now, thus expreſſed by your cheifeſt Antiquary: (<hi>Cambden in Annal. Rer. An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>glic. in Elizabeth pag. 21.22.) Nonnulli ex intimis Conſiliarijs in aures aſsiduè inſuſurrarunt molliſsi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mo ingenio virgini, dum timerent ne animus in du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bio facillimè impelleretur, actum de ipſa &amp; amicis eſſe, conclamatum de Anglia, ſi pontificiam authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tatem in diſpenſando, aut alia quacunque re agnoſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceret: duos pontifices matrem illegittimè Henrico</hi> 8. <hi>emptam pronuntiaſſe, &amp; inde in eorum ſententia iam lata Scotorum Reginam ius in Regnum Angliae ſibi arrogare pontificem ſententiam istam nunquam reſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſſurum.</hi> Some of her inward Counſaylors did dayly whiſper into her eares, beeing a mayden of a moſte tractable diſpoſition, while they fea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red leaſt her minde in doubt might moſt eaſely bee driuen forward (to marry with king Philip of Spayne, and ſoe continue the catholicke Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, that ſhee and her frendes were vndone,
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:14775:59"/>
if ſhee ſhould acknowledge the popes authority in diſpenſeinge or any other matter. For two po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pes had allready pronounced, that her mother was vnlawfully marryed to Henry 8. and ſoe in their ſentence denownced the Queene of Scots did challendge right to the kingdome of En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gland. And that the pope would neuer recall this ſentence.</p>
               <p>And agayne: <hi>Proſpexit huiuſmodi matrimonium ex diſpenſatione contrahendo, non poſſe non agnoſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cere ſeipſam iniuſtis nuptijs natam eſſe. Shee thus perceaued that this marriadge with king Philipp of Spayne her Syſters husband, to bee by the popes diſpenſation, must needs acknowledge that shee was borne in vnlawfull wedlocke.</hi> And they knew al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoe that ſhee remayning a catholicke muſt ſeeke for the popes diſpenſation of this her birth, not onely made and declared illegitimate, by the pope, but by her father himſelfe, and the whole parlament, and Title to the crowne giuen her onely by the will and teſtament of her father, <hi>parlament Henr.</hi> 8. <hi>of Illeg. Lady Elizab.</hi>) againſt which in this caſe your proteſtant h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>an thus exclaymeth: (<hi>Howes histor. preface in Hen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry</hi> 8.) <hi>through feare and terror Henry 8. obteyned an Act of parlament to diſpoſe of the right of ſucceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion to the crowne, and then by his last will and te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stament (K. Henry 8. in his laſt will and Teſtam.) contrary to the law of God, and nature, conuayes it from the lawfull heires of his eldest ſiſter, marryed vnto the kinge of Scotland, vnto the heires of Char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:14775:60"/>
Brandon and others,</hi> (his daughter Elizabeth and of theſe others) <hi>thereby to haue defeated, pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uented and ſuppreſt the vnqueſtionable, and imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diate right from God, of our gratious ſoueraigne, kinge Iames, as if it had beene in the power of his will, or of the parlament, to diſenherite, and preuent the diuine free guift, and grace of almightie God, by which the kings of this land doe hold their crownes.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Thus your proteſtant and priuiledged hiſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rians: by which is euident that this proceedinge by ſuch exorbitant courſes concerning Religio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, was not for loue or likinge of their proteſtant Religion, further then yt gaue them licence and libertie to doe and liue as pleaſed their ſenſuall appetites, which the church and Religion of Rome would not allowe. And yett all theſe ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtre and prophane proceedings not withſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinge, to inſiſt in your proteſtants words in chaungeing Religion in that her parlament. (<hi>Howes hiſtorial. preface. in Q. Elizabeth.) In this parlament notwithſtandinge the preſence of the Queene</hi> (to countenance their bad cauſe) <hi>with the apparant likelyhood of hir longe life, and hope of iſſue to ſucceede her, yett the maior part exceeded the minor but in ſixe voyces, at which time</hi> (to wringe out conſents) <hi>the Queene openly pronoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced, that shee would neuer vexe, or trouble the Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane Catholicks, concerninge any difference in Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion.</hi> Which promiſe of hirs was as well per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed, as that condition of her fathers before,
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:14775:60"/>
of beſtoweinge the church reuenewes, for as your proteſtants haue related, her perſecutions which ſoe vnprincely and vnchriſtianely in her name and power of that ſtraunge claymed ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preamacie in a woman, and ſuch a woman, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>qualed, or exceeded thoſe of Nero, and Diocle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſian, infenſiue tyrants and enemyes of Chriſtia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitie. <hi>Syr Edwyn Sandes in Relation of the ſtate of Religion.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And in that parlament yt ſelfe, where ſhee ſpake theſe words, and proceeded to cruell in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flicted penalties, againſt thoſe Romane Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licks, as all our holy Biſhops were depriued, im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priſoned, or exiled, ſoe were all other eccleſia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſticall parſons that would not doe as pleaſed her. (<hi>Stowe histor. an. 1. Elizab. Holinshed Theater ibid. Cambd. in Annalib. Rerum Anglicarum in Elizab. Parlament.</hi> 1. <hi>Elizabeth.</hi>) greate forfaictures and puniſhments impoſed vppon all, that ſhould heare maſſe, or not bee preſent at her new deui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed ſeruice, premunire, loſſe of lands goods, and perpetuall impriſonment, and loſſe of life alſoe with note of Treaſon, to them that would not acknowledge that ſpirituall ſupreame power in her, of which ſhee was ſoe far vncapable in the iudgment of her owne proteſtants, that diuers of them wrote, and publiſhed to the world, that a woman could not bee a ſupreame gouernor in things temporall; (<hi>Knoxe, Godman and other pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>test. againſt the Regim. of women.</hi>) and they were ſoe violent herein, both in England and Scot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:14775:61"/>
againſt thoſe two bleſſed Queene Maryes: that Q. Mary of England was inforced to make a ſtatute in parlame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, to ſuppreſſe yt: the Abrid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gement thereof is thus. (<hi>parlament</hi> 2. <hi>an.</hi> 1. <hi>Mar. 20. die April. 1554. cap. 2.) The Regall and kingely power of this realme, and all the dignities, and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rogatiues of the ſame, shall bee as wel in a Queene, as in a kinge.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>How the proteſtants in England vpon ſuch good doctrine rebelled againſt that Q. Mary, all knowe; And in Scotland they rather choſed to crowne our Soueraigne in his cradle, then the true Queene his mother ſhould raigne, &amp; haue any power ſpirituall, or temporall at all, in her owne hereditary kingdome, (<hi>Holinsh. histor. of Scotland. Stowe hiſt. an. 1. Iacob.</hi>) but by the vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence of thoſe Scottiſh proteſtants, to bee dri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uert from thence. And landeinge in this king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of England. (<hi>Cambden in Annal. in the life of Q. Mary of Scotland.</hi>) Where by theſe pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtants before ſhee had ſuch iuſt right of ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſion, as they haue declared, &amp; left that moſt vndeniable Title, and intereſt, by which moſte truely, lawfully and vndoubtedly, her ſonne our ſoueraigne kinge Iames now enioyeth both this whole kingdome of Britanie, Ireland, and all the adiacent Ilands by hereditary right from her, ſhee fownde noe further fauour here of the Engliſh proteſtants, but to bee a perpetual pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoner in her life, and to her eternall glory, and engliſh proteſtants ſoe longe endureinge ſhame,
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:14775:61"/>
murthered and martyred at her death. <hi>Stowe Holinsh. Theater of Britanie in Q. Eliz. &amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Moreouer in this ſoe termed parlament, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides the takeinge of this greate and ſupreame ſpirituall chardge and office vnto a woman (ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer heard of in the world before) and ſuppreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſinge of the holy ſacrifice of the maſſe, euer ſince Saint Peters tyme (as before is proued) ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepting three yeares of kinge Edward the 6. a child, and in place thereof admittinge a forme of communion and common prayer neuer vſed by any people catholicks or proteſtants, but in that ſhorte tyme alſoe of that yonge kinge in England, not any one Article of proteſtant Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion eyther againſt the 7. Sacraments of the church, inuocatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of Saints, prayer for the dead, purgatorie, validitie of good workes, merit, iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtification or whatſoeuer els now contradicted by theſe proteſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts, was the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, or vntil the fourth yeare of Q. Elizabeth, concluded by any parla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment proteſtant Authoritie in England, but left arbitrary for euery man to beleeue and practize as his fantaſie ſerued, without any rule at all. <hi>Booke of Articles and Conuocation an.</hi> 1562.</p>
               <p>And for the communion Booke yt ſelfe, it had not any approbation of any one parlament ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, diuine or other, as your proteſtants aſſure vs, but the chardge of making or mareing that was onely committed ſayth your prime proteſtant Antiquary with others, <hi>Cambden annal. pag.</hi> 23. <hi>Parkero, Billo, Maio, Copo, Grindallo whitheado &amp;
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:14775:62"/>
Pilkingtono Theologis, Thomaeque Smitho Equiti: To Parker, Bill, May, Cope, Grindall Whithead and Pil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kington diuines, and Thomas Smyth a knight.</hi> The firſt and cheifeſt of theſe ſeuen beeing Mathew Parker, had beene of ſeuen Religions vnder kinge Henry 8. Edward 6. Q. Mary and Q. Eli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zabeth, chaunging in euery one of thoſe chaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges, as before is proued, (<hi>Godwyne Catalog. of Bish. in Canterbury Matth. Parkr. Foxe to. 2. in k. Henr.</hi> 8. <hi>Edw. 6. Q. Mar. &amp;c.</hi>) and al Q. Maries tyme profeſſinge the catholicke Romane Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion in England, both before and after his de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priuation of his liuings, in the ſecond yeare of Q. Mary for being marryed.</p>
               <p>For the reſt of theſe proteſtant diuines, they were fugitiues for mariadge againſt the canons of the church, and conſpiracy againſt Q. Mary, before which time they were in the ſame diſeaſe of chaungeing Religion with the former prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, and after their going forth of England, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſed the religion, &amp; diſcipline alſo of the puri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tane churches where they liued, namely to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>emplyfie in the liturgie or common booke of prayer of the proteſtants of Franckfort, publiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hed an. 1554. in Q. Maryes tyme, denyinge both the ſupreamacy of temporall princes, and other matters of engliſh proteſtant Religion: this is the ſubſcription of the engliſh proteſtants then in all their names. <hi>(Liturgia ſeu ritus miniſterij in Eccleſia peregrinorum Francofordiae an. 1544. per Petrum Brubachium in fine in ſubſcript.) Subſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bunt
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:14775:62"/>
Angli ob Euangelium profugi totius Eccleſiae ſuae nomine. Iohannes Mackbraeus &amp;c. The prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stants of England that were fled for the Ghoſpell, ſubſcribe in the name of their whole church. Ihon Mackbree minister, Ihon Stanton, William Hamon, Ihon Bendall, William whithingham,</hi> and to aſſure vs that theſe men in particular before named, bee Authors or correctors of yt, &amp; neyther did, nor in their owne iudgment could allowe yt, it is euident: firſt both becauſe they were of this proteſtant Franckford congregation, ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condly becauſe: <hi>The first protestants of this king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome</hi> (your proteſtants words. <hi>Couel in examin. pag.</hi> 72.) <hi>in a letter ſubſcribed with eleuen of their hands, whereof Knoxe, Gilby, whithinghame and Godman were foure, moste of them hauing iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment and learninge, vtterly condemned yt. (Couel a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt Burges pag.</hi> 69.122.47.185.) Soe did Cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uine at Geneua, Ridley your proteſtant Biſhopp and ſuppoſed martyr in a letter to Grindal him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe a cheife agent in it: all the Caluiniſts in the world abrode in their publick confeſſions, and at home haue likewiſe euer, and doe ſtill con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demne it, as alſoe all Lutherans that euer were, and all thoſe writers or correctors of it them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelus, and all the proteſtants in that firſt parla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment in all probable iudgment, except fowre new cownſaylers of Q. Elizabeth, the Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſſe of Northampton, Earle of Bedford, Ihon Grey of Pyrge, and Cecile her <hi>pauculi intimi,</hi> to whome onely (as ſayth your hiſtorian. <hi>Ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>bden
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:14775:63"/>
ſupr. in Annal. in Elizab.</hi>) this matter was com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municated vnto: <hi>re nemini communicata, niſi Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chioni Northamptoniae Comiti Bedfordiae, Iohanni Greio de Pyrgo, &amp; Cecilio.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And this matter was ſufficiently proued by ſome of your late Biſhops in the Conference at Hampton Court, publickly betweene the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtant Biſhops and puritans, before our kinge himſemſelfe; where Barlowe your Biſhop in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lating of that diſputation, <hi>(Barlowe Conference at Hampton Court pag.</hi> 14.<hi>15.)</hi> bringeth in Babing<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton, a proteſtant Biſhop of yours openly to ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge, that in the beginninge, <hi>your proteſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tants religion, and communion booke thereof, was propoſed and approued in that firſt parlament by am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>biguous and indirect dealeinge of the compoſers of that communion booke,</hi> and citeth the Archbiſhop of yorke to that purpoſe. And if wee may be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeue your proteſtant Relations of that diſpute printed with priuiledge, (<hi>Their protestant Rela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of that Confer. printed by Ihon windet cap.</hi> 1.2.3. <hi>all annexed to Barlows Relation.</hi>) wee ar told, that your proteſtant Archbiſhop of Canterbury, Biſhop of London, &amp; Biſhop of Wyncheſter did here vpon their knees before his maieſty confeſſe as much of the errors of that booke, and their Religion: thus wee haue from them in three ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerall relations, and from the fourth by your Biſhop Barlowe as before</p>
               <p>Finallie thus wee pore catholicke preiſts and catholicks haue toyled ourſelues in ſearching,
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:14775:63"/>
ſeeking and preaching all proteſtants procee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dings, parlaments, lawes writings, liues &amp; dea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leings of theſe pretended reformers, and the further wee wade, the deeper wee ar in error, if Catholick Religion could poſſibly bee error; for as is euident before, wee can finde nothing in any of theſe proteſtant patterns and exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples, but ſuch as confirme vs in that faith wee profeſſe with the catholicke chriſtian world in all ages. To which God of his mercy conuert them that bee in error. And ſoe much for this firſt part of this <hi>protestant Plea and petition.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But ſeeing wee cannot finde any comforte by your owne writers and relators of theſe thinges to ioyne with you in your New Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion: wee will next proue vnto you by your owne doctors and Antiquaries, that holy Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion which wee embrace (&amp; for which you per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecute vs) to be the ſame which was firſt prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched here by Saint Peter and his holy diſciples, and ſoe conſequently deliuered by Chriſt him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, and continued in this nation in all ages euen ſince then, vntill theſe tymes.</p>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="approbation">
            <pb facs="tcp:14775:64"/>
            <head>APPROBATIO.</head>
            <p>Ego infraſcriptus legi libellum Angli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>canum cui Titulus praefigitur, <hi>Proteſtants plea and petition for Priests and Papists,</hi> &amp; nihil in eo reperi fidei Catholicae vel bonis moribus aduerſum, quin potius eun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dem vtilem futurum iudico, &amp; dignum qui in lucem prodeat. Datum Duaci 19. Septemb. 1621.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>MATTHAEVS KELLISONVS.</signed>
            </closer>
            <pb facs="tcp:14775:64"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
